I am not a number

Day 00269: Tuesday, 2015 December 01

I remember what I did a couple days ago that I thought was important but could net remember at the time. I read a piece of mail containing one of those "prescreened credit offers". It said that you could opt out of receiving those via telephone. This made me quite annoyed, as you should not require a telephone for opting out of having random companies peruse your credit report and send you junk mail. I did some research, and it turns out that you can also opt out over the Web, as you should be able to. However, the credit prescreening opt-out website has an annoying feature where it checks to make sure you are within the United States before it will allow you to fill out their online form. They do this by checking your IP address, which is an idiotic method. Anyone using Tor is going to have a random global IP address, regardless of where they physically sit. I had to try several times before I could fill out the form completely. For someone using a VPN located outside the country, it might be impossible to fill out the form at all. The blocking of out-of-country IP addresses is made even more idiotic because the form asks for your home address, so they could instead figure out your location from that. There is no need to check your IP address for its location. I mainly only filled out the form to assert that it should be possible to opt out without a telephone. While the form asked for a telephone number, providing one was optional. There were two options for opting out. The first allows you to opt out of these offers, though only for five years. The second allows you to opt out permanently, but but requires physical documents be signed. I chose the five-year opt-out to avoid the paperwork. None of this would be necessary if the credit reporting agencies were not being jerks though. It seems that they are giving lists of potential debtors to credit agencies, and this opt-out form tells the credit reporting agencies to knock it off and get you off the lists that they give out. They should respect people's privacy better and not give out these lists in the first place. Credit agencies should wait for applicants to come to them.

I went shopping today as my vegan food supplies are running a bit low. As I am on foot, I did not get as much as I wanted because I could not carry it all, so I might need to go out again soon. The closest grocery store has one of those tracking programs where if you do not carry one of their purchase-tracking cards with you so they can chain your purchases together, they charge you a higher price for merchandise. Essentially, they are charging customer for the right to privacy. When I shop there, I always ask for a new card. That way, they do not charge me to exercise my right to privacy, but I am able to exercise it none the less. Usually, the customer representative tells me that I can register it with my personal information online, but I do not actually do that. Today, the customer representative instead asked me to fill out the online application in-store using the tablet that the store has set up just for that purpose. I tried to comply, but the form had a telephone number field and would not allow me to leave it blank. I talked to the representative about it, and she just had me abort the registration. Had the registration form allowed me to submit my information without a telephone number, the store would have had my name, email address, and postal address. Because of their demand that I present them with a telephone number, they got nothing. It worked out well for me today, but I do wish that people would get over their obsession with telephone numbers. First of all, not everyone has telephone service. Second, not everyone that *does* have telephone service wants to give out their telephone number, for one reason or another. Some of us have obtuse reasons such as not feeling that it is respectful to ask that we identify as a number, while others simply do not want to deal with telemarketers or even voice calls in general.

Professor Shyguy did not make his original deadline of releasing Fragmentation today, as he said that he might not. He has now moved the deadline to the fifth of this month.

I applied for work at a local meat shop. I must really be desperate. If hired, I will be required to sell corpse flesh all day and act happy about it. That does not seem like my idea of fun.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Endless loops, Facebook policies, and a letter from our ISP

Day 00270: Wednesday, 2015 December 02

Last night, I could not get this website to compile. It seemed to be caught in an endless loop somewhere in one of the scripts. It seemed to somehow be tied to yesterday's weblog entry file, though it did not contain any loops or call any functions that do. This morning, I had time to actually sit down and debug, and it seems that the issue was not caused by any of the content of yesterday's weblog entry file, but rather by its presence. The script used to build the weblog index pages calls \st\y\calendar(), a looping function, in order to build the ASCII calendars with the hyperlinks to individual entry pages. The function stops looping when it comes to the end of a week in which the next week is part of a month that is of a higher month number than the intended month. This was meant to make the function terminate when reaching the next month, but caused a glitch when dealing with the month of December. PHP treats December as month twelve and January as month one, so for the loop to terminate, the loop would need to reach the nonexistent month number thirteen. I speculate that this same issue may have caused a bug in ASCII calendars representing January as well, causing the loop to terminate prematurely due to the preceding month having a higher month number than the intended month. I have now corrected the bug by having the function take into account both the month and the year when deciding when to terminate.

Speaking of the calendar pages, the script that I use to build them will need to be adjusted next month. When I built it, I set it up to use the page at "/weblog/2015/" as the main index page knowing that come 2016, I would want to create a more inclusive index at "/weblog/". I later moved the weblog index to "/en/weblog/2015/" when I moved everything to to "/en/", but the plans for a more inclusive index have not changed.

Even once I had my SRV records set correctly, Hosted.IM was still having trouble seeing that they resolved to the addresses that they wanted them to. It has been several days now though, so they have cleared out the stale records from their system and performed a fresh query. I am now available over XMPP for anyone that would like to contact me that way.

I applied for work at the local convenience store. My mother would not like if I went to work there, but I am running out of options and there is no harm in applying. If I get the interview and they end up wanting to hire me, I will discuss it with her and and decide whether or not to take the position. After registering an account with the convenience store job website, they sent me a link to register for some sort of Employer collective. I do not know how effective this was though, there seem to be no login credentials associated with the accounts there, so I cannot check on the status of my application.

Wowaname told me today that Facebook's policies regarding legal names have changed recently, saying that they now make exceptions. However, when I asked about it, she said that to get an exception, you must first go against the policy, then get caught and make an appeal explaining why you did not use your legal name on your Facebook account. This is not good enough; one must be allowed to create an account under their preferred name instead of their legal name, knowing that this will be fine from the start. I did a little research on Facebook policy, and while I did not find any information about this appeal process, I did find information on proving your identity to Facebook. It appears that it is possible to use your real name even if it is not your legal name, though you need to cough up more personal information than I care to. First of all, this does not get you out of Facebook's date of birth requirement. As far as I am concerned, Facebook does not need this information. Second, you need three forms of identification. The first two forms of identification must have your preferred name on them. The third can have a different name, such as your legal name, but must have either a photograph of you or have your date of birth. I could easily meet these requirements. I receive my mail under the name Yst Dawson and my credit card is under this same name. Both of these are listed as valid forms of identification. As for the third item, I could submit my government-issued identification card that instead of having my real name, has my legal name. However, I again feel that this is going too far. If Facebook wants my legal name, they will have to put in the minimal effort needed to run a whois query on my domain. (Further reading revealed that Facebook allows the covering up of extra information present on the identification documents that are not needed for verification. The examples mentioned included covering up your Social Security number or credit card number, but as the state-issued identification card contains a legal name, date of birth, and photograph and only one of these is needed, the photograph and legal name can be covered up.) Besides, registering a Facebook account over Tor seems to require verification of a telephone number these days, and I absolutely refuse to give Facebook a telephone number, even just a burner number.

Our ISP wrote today that someone in our household downloaded something illegally. They did not say what that illegal thing was though, so we were unable to determine which of us downloaded it. I know that it was not me for two reasons. First, I only download things that are under licenses that allow redistribution. Second, my traffic is behind three or seven encrypted proxies at all times, so the ISP does not see what I am doing. One good thing did come of this though: I managed to talk Cyrus into routing his Web traffic though Tor. Vanessa is still convinced that using Tor is incredibly difficult, despite my repeated reassurances, but once Cyrus sees how pretty much nothing has changed over Tor, he can help me convince Vanessa. I will not even try with our mother though, at least for now. She is far too against pretty much anything relating to anticensorship, online privacy, and freedom. If the ISP is going to be this way though, there is no way that I can run a Tor exit node here.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Workflow, fairies, and aeronautical, advertised sorrows

Day 00271: Thursday, 2015 December 03

I went through my password database to make sure that all my public accounts are listed on my contact page. I came across my Geocaching account, but I do not want to link to the Geocaching website though, as they do not allow logging over Tor. I was about to delete my account, but instead, decided to open a support ticket about the issue. Depending on how they respond, I will either add my Geocaching account to the list of places to find me or I will close the account.

My search for a way to create decent onion address keys continues. Today, I came up with a new solution, one that is much more automated than my last. Previously, I was throwing a dictionary at eschalot and having it use word list mode to find onion addresses in which the first eight or more characters form a word. This has the obvious disadvantage that the end of the onion address is still random and often unreadable. The onion addresses generated must all be reviewed for readability by hand. I tried compressing an entire dictionary into a regular expression so I could require that the pattern of words repeat from beginning to end, but the regular expression was too large and eschalot could not handle that much input. My new solution is to instead focus on only words that are four characters long. between the fact that only so many four-letter words exist and the fact that the onion address's second level is divisible by four so I do not need to include words of another length, the regular expression was kept small enough for eschalot to handle. I tried using eight-character words instead of four-character words for better memorability, but that regular expression was too large. I was able to include all available sixteen-character words in my four-character word regular expression though, so if eschalot chances upon such a rare gem, it will not just be thrown out. While I still think that my solution needs some major reworking before it can be considered the optimal choice, it is the first solution that I have come up with that I feel is worth sharing. I call it fouroni; "four" being a reference to the fact that it uses four four-letter words and "oni" being the only three letters in the //onion. TLD. It actually spits out onion addresses at a reasonable rate, too; you only have to wait a few minutes to get your first address key.

Before touching up fouroni enough to upload, I mentioned my new solution to creating readable onion addresses on #tor. Only one person responded, and cacahuatl did not thing that it was a good idea. Instead, cacahuatl thought the proper solution was to translate onion addresses from their naturally-unreadable state into some sort of human-recognizable code, for lack of a better term. The idea is to convert each onion address into a phrase of five English words that can be translated back losslessly. The project that accomplishes this appears to be derived from a project that losslessly translates an onion addresses into a phrase of six English words, though as the license of the newer project is incompatible with that of the first project, it may be a complete recoding of the project. When I mentioned that this solution would be great for verifying onion addresses but would not help with hyperlinks or Web browser address bars, cacahuatl said that this should be fixed with a Web browser plugin. I disagree. If a Web browser plugin is used, it will mean writing pages that depend on nonstandard domains. Instead, what should happen if this method of making onion addresses readable is to be used, is write them into Tor's URI handler itself. For example, if leekspeak translates authorednansyxlu.onion into the phrase "workflow fairies aeronautical advertised sorrows", perhaps Tor should map workflow-fairies-aeronautical-advertised-sorrows.leek.onion to authorednansyxlu.onion.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

It is possible to become free of your Social Security number

Day 00272: Friday, 2015 December 04

My project from yesterday creates pronounceable onion addresses, but the onion addresses it produces are not easily *readable*. It is hard to see where one word ends and another starts. I am not sure if this is because the words are so short or because there are so many words present without any spaces between them. Today, I put together a new project that tackles the problem in a different way. The first version of it uses eschalot to search for onions beginning with eight-letter words and saves them to disk. A second script is then used to check the second half of the onion address to see if it is also an eight-letter word. I quickly decided to rework the code and and complicate it a bit. The new version uses eschalot to search for onion addresses starting with words eight to sixteen characters long, once again saving them to disk. The second script can then be used to compare the onion address against a series of word lists to determine the length of the initial word. The remaining part of the onion address is then compared against the word lists to see if it makes up a single word, and throws out any addresses that does not make the cut. It no doubt still trows out many pronounceable onion addresses, but at least this system does not require hand-sorting thousands of onion addresses spit out by eschalot. So far, the scripts have not judged any onion addresses to be usable, so perhaps they are too strict.

I stumbled upon information today that said that one can have their Social Security number revoked. When I think about the fact that I even have a Social Security number, it makes me a bit angry. The Enumeration at Birth Program was used to trick my parents into thinking that they had to get a Social Security number assigned to my siblings an I, as it has been used to trick many parents and as it was set up to do. I do not want a Social Security number though, and view the thing as a curse, not a boon. I thought that the assignment was irreversible; that I was stuck with this number forever. However, it seems that by sending a letter to the right place, I can fix this stupid mess. I will not act just yet, my mother would probably be pissed off if she ended up thinking that she needed my Social Security number for something later. I will get this fixed in due time though.

From the sound of it, I may be headed back to Springfield again with my mother tomorrow, depending on her energy level. The primary goal this time will not be hauling stuff home, though we will no doubt do that too, but to get the house cleaned up enough for a real estate broker to come in.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Cepo

Day 00274: Sunday, 2015 December 06

It seems that my new computer's name was your-588b4a13ea. That name will not do at all, so I will be renaming it after all. Upon installing the Wi-Fi card that I took from chicken, the machine would not boot at all. Instead of showing the usual BIOS screen, the monitor showed no picture and the machine just repeatedly beeped at me. I tried booting it a couple more times, but it was no use. While disappointed that my Wi-Fi card seemed to be broken enough to prevent booting, this problem seemed very similar to chicken's problem: it will not show any picture, leading me to believe that it is not functional. Hoping that the Wi-Fi card was indeed the issue, I tried booting chicken without it. No good. chicken stayed as dark as ever. So of course, I tried booting the new machine again, with the Wi-Fi card still in. Not only did the machine boot without issue, Windows detected new hardware, no doubt the Wi-Fi card. I have no idea what the problem is, but it appears to be gone. Just so that this weblog entry would not make it appear that I was not trying what appeared to be the obvious other solution, I tried using the new monitor that came with the new machine with chicken. As the monitor is not the issue, that did not help.

When I named my past computers, I was both unaware that they automatically used permutations of their names within the //local. name space for mDNS or that //local. names used for mDNS are valid names. As such, I just kind of used whatever names I felt like. However, now knowing this, I consulted RFC 1178 for advice. One thing that it said was to limit name length to eight characters, so the name that I considered yesterday, "insulo de aspiri", is too long. I also did more looking into the word "aspiri", and it seems to have a meaning closer to "aspire" than "hope". This is an old machine and it is trapped behind a restrictive ISP. I do not expect it to become something amazing. Its job is simply to provide me with a base of operations to work from in onion space; to act as a second home, seeing as my main home, //y.st., cannot be properly utilized under the restrictive policies of my ISP. If I later find a way to do something amazing on this machine later, that is all well and good, but my hope for this machine is quite humble. There are no real aspirations at work here. I instead named it cepo, meaning "onion" in Esperanto.

The installation went smoothly, and the amd64 installer was even able to detect and use the Wi-Fi card to retrieve needed packages from the Web. Unfortunately, once the system was installed and booted, it was not using the Wi-Fi card by default. I managed to get the Wi-Fi card online after much struggling with the help of a guide, though the guide seems to be incomplete. It says to edit the /etc/network/interfaces file and add a "wireless-mode [MODE]" line, among other things. However, it gives no indication as to what [MODE] should be. After setting [MODE] to several different strings, I found a hint in a topic about Raspbian. The example configuration that was posted there had the [MODE] set to "managed", so I tried that, and it seems to work. My home network's name, chosen by my mother, has a space in it, so I put quotation marks around the name in that file. It seems that this is unnecessary and counterproductive. Spaces are already treated as literal and so were the quotation marks. With the quotation marks removed, everything now works.

The next problem was the lack of mDNS support by default. For some reason, when I install Debian with a desktop, mDNS support comes preinstalled, but when I do not install a desktop, the package needed to provide mDNS needs to be installed manually. Come to think of it, at least one of my old installs without a desktop had mDNS support by default, as when I descovered mDNS support in Debian, I tested it on what was then my server, chicken. Instructions for enabling mDNS support in Debian said to install the avahi-daemon, avahi-discover, and libnss-mdns packages, which seems to have worked perfectly.

Apache was not playing nicely today, just like last time that i had to configure it. After hours of debugging, I finally found one problem. The files in /etc/apache2/sites-enabled/ are only read if their names end in ".conf". This limitation did not exist in past versions, and I do not know why it was added. However, renaming the file was not all that was needed to make Apache read it. After a lot more struggling, I gave up. Wowaname convinced me to switch to NGINX. NGINX does not have PHP support, which could be problematic later, but at least I got the onion website back up off the ground. Wowaname walked me through it and showed me a few example configuration files. Getting NGINX to function was still a struggle though. I am not convinced that NGINX is easier to use by much, if at all.

Transferring the onion to another machine disrupted use of TorChat at first. I thought that all I had to do was configure the onion address to point not at localhost, but at cepo's LAN IP address. However, changing some settings in TorChat's configuration fixed the issue. The main problem now is that the TorChat client now listens to any connection from a machine on the local network that claims to be TorChat's onion and this connection is on the post-decryption side. I thought that it already did this, so there was no further venerability (aside from the unencrypted messages being exposed on the LAN), but TorCHat does not listen to connections from other machines by default. Another issue is that while I look like I am online at all times, I really am not. If you send me a message while I am offline, the message is lost instead of being saved on the sender's side until I return. While I setting up Tor on cepo to host the onion address, I also set it to act as a Tor relay node. I do not dare set it to run as an exit node though with my ISP being on the offensive. THere are rules to running multiple Tor relays, and while I cannot be expected to know them all yet, I do know that if you run multiple relays, you are to set some sort of "family" variable to indicate that the relays are run by the same entity to prevent multiple relays run by the same entity from being used in a single circuit. Orbot's interface does not have the option to do that, and Orbot seems to ignore the extra configuration lines option, so I simply shut down that relay. As long as I am only running one relay, I do not have to worry about the multi-relay rules. If I get a second full server up some time, I can worry about running multiple relays and following the multi-relay rules at that time. Besides, Orbot acting as a relay was seriously impacting my mobile's battery life, so it will be nice to not have to charge the thing as often now.

This website is a mess. The combination of the split darknet/clearnet website model combined with the change in onion address when that was over has done a number on it. Many hyperlinks are broken, and I really need to get all of that fixed before the first of December. When the first hits, all pages will receive an update to the "Weblog" hyperlink at the top of the page, triggering a signature recalculation site-wide. Any page that has to be updated after that point will stand out to anyone that actually checks signatures and knows how to read the signing date. I might as well take this time to also build the index page for /en/weblog/. It does not hurt to have that out early as long as I do not directly link to it. (it is fine if people visit that page, it just cannot be the main weblog index.)

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Setting up ownCloud

Day 00275: Monday, 2015 December 07

I went to install ownCloud today, but it seems to have a dependency on Apache. The package information says that ownCloud can use either the apache2 or httpd. httpd is a virtual package provided by the apache2 package, but it is also provided the nginx-full package, which I installed yesterday. Theoretically, Aptitude should not have tried to install Apache. In any case, it seemed that I would need to set up Apache if I was to use ownCloud for the time being.

Yesterday, wowaname talked about the importance of running every onion website on a different port to prevent spoofing attacks that make use of the host name header. As such, I set NGINX up on a nonstandard port and set Tor to direct port 443 connections to this other port. Knowing that NGINX was running on a nonstandard port so Apache would not clash with it, I reinstalled Apache. Somehow, Apache functioned correctly using the same configuration files that were not working yesterday. I have no idea what could have possibly have changed. The only issue came when I tried to configure Apache to use the port that Tor is redirecting connections to. I had forgotten that NGINX was still bound to this port. After shutting NGINX down, Apache bound to the port correctly and everything is running fine. Why could it not have been this easy yesterday?

I decided to set up ownCloud's database the easy way, so I tried to install phpMyAdmin. I ran into difficulties when setting it up though. The install scripts from the phpMyAdmin package wanted to set up phpMyAdmin's database, but it kept failing to connect to the local database server. Eventually, I located the issue: while phpMyAdmin requires a local instance of MySQL in order to function, it does not depend on the MySQL server package.

I found out that every Tor relay node can be looked up online. My node should be listed, but for whatever reason, it is not. I restarted my relay while debugging, so it might mess with the uptime stat, but everything on my end looks fine. The error log says Dec 07 19:14:35.000 [notice] Self-testing indicates your ORPort is reachable from the outside. Excellent. Publishing server descriptor., so my relay should be reachable from the outside world.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Groundspeak is in favor of government surveillance

Day 00276: Tuesday, 2015 December 08

My main goal for today was to get my calendar synchronized between my mobile and ownCloud on cepo. Unfortunately, I had misplaced (and potentially deleted) my backed up calendar data from chicken's ownCloud instance, so my only copy of my calendar data was on the mobile. I quickly found that Replicant does not offer a way to back up your calendar data to a file, an issue that it inherited from Android. I managed to find a third-party application that provides the feature, but ownCloud could not import the calendar file that the mobile application exported. There was no error message provided by ownCloud, it just acted like I had not initiated the import. I eventually got around this limitation by importing the calendar data to the new synchronized calendar using the same application that I had exported it with.

DAVdroid, the mobile application that I use to synchronize my calendar (and contact list) has issues as well. Do not get me wrong, it is the best option that seems to be available, but getting it set up is a pain. First, it refuses to synchronize over a connection that is encrypted using an "untrusted" TLS certificate. In other words, DAVdroid would rather use a completely unencrypted and vulnerable connection than deal with a certificate that it does not like. It does not even offer an option to override this behavior. The author of this application created a second application to try to lessen the annoyance of this anti-feature: CAdroid. CAdroid downloads certificates from services so that you may import them into your local "trusted" certificate store. This is no substitute for a basic override option, but it gets the job done. I am not trying to verify identity with the certificate, I am only trying to fend off passive eavesdropping. Besides, some of the well-known and "trusted" certificate authorities have issued bogus certificates in the past. The trust model is flawed and should not be shoved down our throats. In any case, CAdroid refused to download my certificate from my owncloud domain because while the owncloud domain is on a subdomain of my main onion address, my certificate claims only to be valid for the second-level onion domain itself. Luckily, this certificate was also in use on the domain that it claimed to be for, so I just downloaded it from there, but I feared that DAVdroid would refuse this certificate. Both applications were written by the same author, so if the one refused to even download the certificate from the "incorrect" domain, would the other not refuse to *use* the certificate with that same "invalid" domain? I was fortunate enough to be wrong though. DAVdroid did put up a fuss about the certificate not matching the domain, but it did offer an override option as long as the certificate was in my local "trusted" certificate database.

The next issue with DAVdroid is not even an issue with the application itself, but with the Android platform. DAVdroid has added support for an application called Tasks. If Tasks is installed, DAVdroid can synchronize to do lists over calDAV in addition to its regular calendar synchronization. The catch is that due to a bug in Android (which was inherited by Replicant), the order that applications are installed matters. To add to do list support in DAVdroid, one must first install Tasks, then remove and reinstall DAVdroid. This seems easy enough, but due to my higher-security-than-default settings, there were complications. After doing this, calendars were no longer being synchronized. The mobile said that no calendars were available! I tried removing both applications and reinstalling only DAVdriod, but the issue persisted. I eventually remembered that DAVdroid needed to have PrivacyGuard turned off in order to function. While I had PrivacyGuard turned off for DAVdroid before, removing and reinstalling it had switched it back on, as all new applications on my mobile have PrivacyGuard activated by default. If Android (and therefore Replicant) was not being picky about the order in which applications were installed, PrivacyGuard would never been switched back on for DAVdroid and everything would have gone smoothly.

Groundspeak finally got back to me after almost a week, and said that The Geocaching website is not available over Tor. I already knew this, and I had originally asked them if there was any way that they would consider easing up on this restrictive policy. I decided to just tell them that I was saddened by their support of surveillance and that I would choose a different hobby. I half expect them to write back saying that they are not in favor of surveillance, but any policy that is against Tor use is in favor of government surveillance. If they do not write back, I will drop the issue, but if they write back saying that they are not in favor of surveillance, I will write back with a verbose response explaining that they cannot be anti-Tor without being pro-surveillance. It simply is not possible.

I made the mistake of telling my mother about the news with Groundspeak. She had been the one to suggest that I contact them in the first place, so I thought that it would be a good idea to let her know how that had went. Bad idea. First, she got pissed off that I would rather avoid logging Geocache finds than drop my proxy, as if my not logging finds was some sort of attack on her. Then she went off about all the other things that makes her angry about me. She is mad that I am asexual, claiming that it is a bad attitude, as if it is not just an innate part of what I am like any other sexual orientation. She is mad that I do not have a child by now, when she was already six months pregnant at my age. She is mad that I am vegan, as she does not like people having a different diet than her in her household. She is mad that I hang out with friends online, saying that online friends are not real friends and are a bad influence on me. She is mad that I do not drive a motor vehicle. She is mad that I listen to free music, as if my choice in music has any impact on her. She is mad that I use free software, prefering that I my computer fight me the way that her's constantly fights her. She is mad that in the past, I went through a phase where I drew a lot of pixel art, somthing that i no longer do and no longer have time for, but that she thinks that I should have never done in the first place. She is mad that I quit working with stained glass, a hobby that I once had, but grew out of. She is mad that I do not have a cellular telephone so that she can pester me with text messages, because sending text messages to an email address is somehow so hard for her. She is mad that the mobile that i did choose to get was not an iPhone and not on the Verizon network. She is mad that I eat junk food, though it is not just that she wants me to give up potato chips. She also wants me to eat foods that would make me sick: meat and milk. She is mad that I set up two credit union accounts in Springfield, as if that is any of her business. And she is mad that I am learning Esperanto, a language that she considers useless. She is mad about several other things as well, though I cannot remember what they all are, as she went on for at least an hour. I desperately wanted to take notes, but that would have probably sent her further off the deep end.

I will see if I can use what I have learned to appease her. First, I will try even harder not to mention anything about my days to her. Nothing good ever comes of it, and she is a walking land mine that I might step on if I mention anything that I have done or anything that I feel. I will not drop Tor as my proxy, it is a very important tool against surveillance. However, I will make no mention of it again, make no mention of being blocked from anything again, try not to make any mention of things on the Internet again, and if it comes up, I will lie and say that I have dropped the proxy. Being asexual is not something that I can change, or even that i would ever want to change. Nor will I ever have children. Nothing can be done on this front. If going non-vegan would somehow allow me to live forever, I admit, I would do it. But if I have to die eventually anyway, even if I would live a millennium, I would rather die prematurely than go non-vegan and then die later. If prodded to eat non-vegan foods, I will state this preference for death, hopefully getting my point across. She wants companionship in eating, so I will try simply being in the room while she eats, unable to touch any of the food myself. I will make no mention of my friends again. If it comes up, I will lie and say that I no longer speak with any of them. I have gone through the driver manual several times already, and I will suck it up and take the test. While I refuse to drive on my own behalf, I will drive on her's when requested. Though before I do that, I need to find a local photography studio, as I grew my hair out upon her request just so that she could get a photograph of me with her preferred hair style. I do not want to be stuck with such a photograph for eight years on my identification though, so I need to get the photograph then cut my hair before taking the test. I will make no mention of music again. I will pretend that I have no interest in music whatsoever. I cannot pretend to be interested in proprietary music, the effect on my mind would not be worth it, but I can avoid listening to music when she is around and pretend not to listen to music at all. I will do my best not to mention free software, or software of any kind. Obviously, mention of software may come up because of how prevalent it is in our lives, but I will keep such talk to a minimum. I cannot do anything about the pixel art. I no longer produce it, I cannot do anything about the fact that she is still mad that I ever did. There is likewise no time for stained glass work, especially with all the wasted time spent pretending to be what I am not. I will discuss with her tomorrow about getting a device and plan that she finds suitable and keep my Replicant fairly hidden. I will stop eating junk food. I will try to eat only healthy potato products such as mashed potatoes without added oils, milk replacement products such as soy and almond milk, B vitamin supplements (without them, I will damage my brain and get killer headaches), products that I can clearly see are plants without reading labels such as salads and apples, and protein supplements if needed. I will mention finances as little as possible. There is no need for her to know if I have multiple financial accounts or not. And I will practice Esperanto only when she is not around, pretending to have quit if need-be.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

I want a DNS server

Day 00277: Wednesday, 2015 December 09

Josh Woodward released a Christmas song called My Christmas List. I am not Christian and I do not celebrate holidays in general, butthe message and tune of this song are nice anyway. For Christmas, all he wants is a little peace; peace would be nice. Professor Shyguy released Fragmentation today too. I do not feel up to listening to the full album today though, it has been a long day and one song is about all I can take. I might listen to it in the comming days depending on my mood and depending on if anyone is around.

Wowaname went offline for the fist part of today. Her website was down, my website was down, and her IRC server was down. It seems that her VPS just went down on her for some reason. I did not ask why though, she tends to get touchy when people start asking about technical difficulties.

Now that my ownCloud instance is back up, I once again need an email client that has CardDAV support. If I recall, Evolution has issues, but it does support both CardDAV and PGP encryption, and I do not think I ever found any other email client with CardDAV support to choose from. When setting it up, Evolution refused to allow me to skip the part where I configure it to connect to a server. It is stupid when email clients do that. I needed to configure the proxy settings before I could allow it to reach a remote server. Luckily, Evolution allowed me to enter bogus values when setting it up instead of trying to connect before allowing me to continue. I am not yet ready to put my contacts back online, but I do want to start getting used to Evolution again.

I looked into transferring my credits from my old school to the local community collage, but there was no information on their website about how to determine which of your credits are eligible for transfer. I found a contact email address, though I think that it was the wrong one for this sort of problem, so I asked if the recipient could either help or direct me to someone that could.

I have presented my mother with two options as to mobile devices that she can get me based on what she has said. She really seems to want me to have an iPhone, despite the fact that I have often talked about how awful I think that they are and the fact that they do not do any of the things that I expect of my mobile. She has expressed concern about the price of the iPhone, because she thinks that if I had gotten one when she had wanted me to, then it would have been gratis. However, it would have come with a two-year contract and would have had a raised bill during those two months. Not only does the price in dollars still exist, you also sell away your freedom. The budget-friendly option I suggested was a $10 USD Android that would only cost $20 USD every three months to maintain, a much cheaper device and monthly fee than the carrier that she wants me on. The second option was an iPhone under $45 USD, which would pay for itself in a few months by being off-contract and getting the lower monthly rate compared to the contract option that she wanted me on before. She expressed concerns that the cheap iPhone was several models older than hers, asking me if it would fit my needs with it being so old. I did not know how to respond. If I reminded her that no iPhone of any model can meet any of my needs, she would have flown off the deep end, so I simply replied that I was unsure. I have told her several time in the past that she can do whatever she wants mobile-wise with me, every time that she has complained about my choice in mobiles and mobile plans, but she keeps not making any moves and then complaining to me again. This time, I have presented her with options, so if she fails to make any choices and complains to me again, I will remind her that I am waiting on her decision before I can act.

I tried to find a photography studio with reasonable rates, but most of the ones that I could find did not list prices. One had a formatted price list, but the spot where the prices themselves should have been was just blank. The only photography studio that I could find with actual prices listed had very high prices, though my mother said that this was normal. Why do people waste their money on this sort of thing?

I learned an important lessen about //localhost. today. If you care whether IPv4 or IPv6 is used, specify the IP address, not the host name. Evolution was having issues using Tor today because it was using the IPv6 loopback address and I do not have IPv6 service. I prefer names over numbers, but sometimes it is more effective to work with numbers when you need to configure things.

I am considering setting up a local DNS server to help me learn more about DNS. For a long time, DNS has been important to me, as names are very powerful things and to own a name is to be reachable. I decided to go through the information on special-use domain names so that I would know exactly which names I am officially allowed to commandeer with my DNS server and not. The first thing that I found is that //254.169.in-addr.arpa. is not included with the rest of the special-use IPv4 addresses. While I can use the other special-use rDNS blocks in conjunction with my name server, //254.169.in-addr.arpa. is instead reserved for use in mDNS, the way that I had originally thought that all the special-use rDNS blocks were reserved. Additionally, all special-use IPv6 rDNS blocks are reserved for use with mDNS. My guess is that the reason that I do not have matching multicast rDNS functionality to go with my regular mDNS functionality is that my Wi-Fi router operates in the 10.0.0.* range and the 10.*.*.* range's rDNS blocks are reserved for local name servers, not mDNS rDNS lookups. I decided to put up a page sorting the different special-use domain names by their general implementation. It seems that the only available TLD for personal network use is //test., so I will use that domain block as well as the //10.in-addr.arpa. block for use for the network's rDNS.

I found a couple interesting things while working on that tiny research project. First, the classification of the //onion. TLD as special is no longer a draft; it is not an official standard according to the IETF, complete with its own RFC. Second, I found that RFC 6761 is inconsistent. According to this RFC, if a special domain can be implemented using standard DNS registration, then it is not actually special at all and should not be defined as such. It then goes on to specify four different domains as special and says that the special way that they need to be handled is to not treat them any different than regular DNS names and that they are registered in the name of IANA, who hosts Web pages at those names explaining their use (only three of these names are actually registered by IANA and have this webpage). The RFCs are supposed to define our standards, but it seems that they are not always even consistent with themselves.

Shinra, a new user in #Volatile, offered to list my onion address on his/her Tor classifieds page. Only after I accepted did I see that the website charges a modest fee. He.she has said nothing since I told him/her my onion address, so I do not know if he/she is actually going to charge me. If so, I suppose I will pay, but only if I can use a basic credit card. I do not yet know how to use any crypto-currencies.

The power went out for a few minutes, knocking cepo and this website offline. Not wanting to disturb my sleeping family, I will not get the server started back up unill tomorrow morning.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

_services._dns-sd._udp.local.

Day 00278: Thursday, 2015 December 10

I did some research today looking for a setting in Debian to make <a href="/en/domains/cepo.local.xhtml">cepo automatically boot back up after a power failure. I figured that it was a long shot to think that the operating system would have that level of control over the machine when powered off, but as the operating system can have the machine come back online after a reboot (instead of having the operating system shut the machine down, then needing the user to hit the power bullon to turn the machine back on), it might be possible. I never did find such a setting in the operating system, but I did find that many BIOSes have such an option. It was a bit of a pain to pull cepo out of the place I stashed it so I could connect it to a monitor and keyboard and take a look, but it payed off. The article said that older BIOSes do not have this option, so I was worried that cepo might not, but cepo was not as old as I had feared.

I found a new tool today called mdns-scan. I do not yet fully understand the output, but it is successfully finding the powered-on machines that I know use mDNS:

+ Zero [00:1f:3a:77:67:48]._workstation._tcp.local
+ Zero._udisks-ssh._tcp.local
+ newdawn [00:19:7e:92:0d:8d]._workstation._tcp.local
+ cepo [00:11:50:d3:e0:11]._workstation._tcp.local

Zero is Vanessa's laptop, which she left on when she left for school. I do not seem to be able to connect to any of those four apparent host names in the usual ways, so I am not sure if they are actually host names or just formatted somewhat like host names. The bracketed segment of these results seem to be the MAC addresses of our machines. It seems that the _udisks-ssh segment of the apparent host name is associated with a remote disk management application that Vanessa must have installed and I do not.

It seems that the method of retrieving the list of local network services is fairly simple. rDNS is implemented by reformatting an IP address into a host name and issuing a PTR DNS record request on the resulting host name. The returned record is supposed to be the host name associated with the IP address. In mDNS service discovery, a similar method is used. The querying machine issues a PTR record query to the broadcast IP address requesting information about //_services._dns-sd._udp.local. and any machine can answer with one or more host names. The returned host names seem to represent services that are available, though it seems that perhaps the returned host names are not the names that said machines will actually respond to, instead being more like descriptions of the services provided. This service-discovery method seems to be based on a more general specification not specific to mDNS, though I do not seem to be able to get it to work with other domains.

I initially had some problems passing DNS queries through cepo so that cepo could return responses for //test. and //10.in-addr.arpa. names. The issue was that either cepo would not pass queries that it did not have answers about onto the next DNS server or that such queries ended up creating a loop, as the router would ask the cepo, which would then ask the router, and so on. I am guessing that it was the former though, and queries just were not being forwarded at all. I found a DNS query forwarding tutorial that helped me solve the problem. It was written for Ubuntu, but it works just as well on Debian. I used Google's DNS servers as the servers to query in case of zones that my server is not authoritative for, which is unfortunate, but it is better than using my ISP's DNS servers. My ISP captures invalid domains and redirects them to their partner's advertisement server. I have not yet made my server authoritative for any zones yet, but just having the network set up so that DNS queries pass through cepo without breaking anything is a good start.

After changing the router settings a few times, I found that when the router goes down, cepo does not reconnect to it. This is a big problem, especially considering that cepo is now handling all DNS requests for all non-Tor users on the network. If cepo goes down, it is as if the network connection is down for my family. Somiaj from #Tor suggested using wpasupplicant in roaming mode to make cepo reconnect automatically. I found a guide for configuring roaming mode in wpasupplicant, but it did not seem to offer working instructions. After finally getting everything working with help from a second guide, I noticed that I had missed something from the first. Following the first guide's instructions seems to give a better setup in my opinion, though somewhere along the way, I ended up using auto wlan0</code instead of allow-hotplug wlan0. https://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/debian-reference/ch05.en.html#_the_basic_syntax_of_etc_network_interfacesIf I understand correctly, allow-hotplug is used when the Wi-Fi card will actually be added and removed from the machine while running, while auto is used to make the interface start up when the machine boots.

Cepo's Wi-Fi card does not seem physically sound. It was broken in the past, but I fixed it with pliers, thinking that that was the end of that. However, the antenna fell off again today and I had to once more squeeze the thing back together with pliers. Hopefully this will not be a frequent occurrence, especially with it currently residing on a high-up shelf that no one can reach without a stepping stool. It is out of the way and should not get bumped often.

The person at the local community collage I wrote to got back to me today. As I expected, she was not the correct person to contact, but also as expected, she knew who I did need to contact. I have written to this second person now, so I hope to see what needs to be done soon.

I believe that I have removed all hyperlinks from this website that use the quystystxtvdgyst.onion. domain. Hopefully, no other dead links exist on this website, at least not dead links involving my own domains. Maybe tomorrow, I will work on getting the new weblog index page set up.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

//test. and //10.in-addr.arpa.

Day 00279: Friday, 2015 December 11

I received a response about transferring credits, but I the person I wrote to misunderstood. She said that I needed to contact my old school and ask them which credits I can transfer. She had misunderstood which direction I was trying to transfer my credits. I wrote back to clarify, and she understood the second time. She said that all credits could be transferred in, but that was possible that only some would count toward a degree at the school that she represents. I asked how to tell how many credits were usable and how many courses I would need to complete my degree, so directed me to a third person. She only gave me a telephone number for third person, so I explained that I do not have a telephone and asked how to reach him by email. It seems that he is not reachable by email though, so she gave me the email address of yet a fourth person with which to make an appointment to come in in person.

I updated the weblog index-building script. Not only does it now take care of the main, multi-year spanning index, it also includes the year on the ASCII calendars to make navigating the new main index easier.

I think that I have come up with the format that I want to use for resolved rDNS host names on my local network. My main goal is to learn how to run a DNS server for both forward and backward name resolution, but as a secondary goal, I want to set up a clean structure that will make it easier to manage the Wi-Fi router's whitelist. By combining the whitelist feature and the router's static DHCP allocation option, I can assign permanent IP addresses to any host that I allow on the network. I can then use rDNS resolution to find out what device has a given IP address and who that device belongs to, making it easier to find out which devices are no longer around and should be removed from the whitelist. The format that I currently want to use for rDNS return values is "{device name}.{owner name}.[no-mdns.]in-addr.test." If I know that, for example, Vanessa only has her laptop and there are three devices associated with her, I can remove the other two from the whitelist and DNS server. Likewise, if I see a device that I do not recognize on the whitelist, I can check to see who owns or owned it. The no-mdns segment is just a flag to myself. I doubt that it will come in handy, but any host that does not answer to a //local. domain will be given this designation.

Quite a while ago, I set our Wi-Fi router to reserve the shortest nine available local IP addresses for my personal use. I wanted to be able to assign these IP addresses to my machines so that the router's DHCP server would always assign my machines the same addresses and I could find them accross the network when I needed them. This was before I learned that mDNS was being used by all of my machines and that I did not need static IP addresses for any machine that I was not port forwarding to. rDNS is pretty meaningless without static IP addresses though, so because all IP addresses will now be static, reserving the short addresses for static use is pointless. Instead, I am now reserving the larger address range from 10.0.0.1 to 10.0.0.99 for use by any machine that answers to an mDNS domain. Any that do not will instead be assigned an IP address with three digits in its least-significant segment. I have also reallocated chicken's and thinkpad-x60s's IP addresses (10.0.0.1 and 10.0.0.2, respectively) to Vanessa's and Cyrus' machines. Cleaning out the old whitelist meant removing machines that were no longer in use on the network.

I found a guide to configuring Bind9 and used it to set up zones for both the //test. and //10.in-addr.arpa. name spaces. At first, only the //test. zone functioned. I spent quite a bit of time trying to figure out what was wrong with the //10.in-addr.arpa. zone file, but it turned out that there was nothing wrong with that file itself. Instead, the problem was in the configuration file that told Bind9 where to even locate the file.

I received a letter written in Arabic from a company today. It seems that someone once again used one of my email addresses to register an account. Luckily, the email contained instructions for having that account deleted, though on second thought, I should have just sent a password reset request and added the account to my collection of accounts that people gave me by using my email address to register instead of their own.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

An adult coloring club

Day 00280: Saturday, 2015 December 12

I started out my day helping my mother in her classroom again. We did not stay long this time though. After that, we went to an adult coloring club meet-up at the local library. It appears that while today, the first meet-up, was scheduled on the second Saturday of the month, subsequent meet-ups will occur on the third Saturday of each month. Even if she does not go, I think that I will attempt to attend these, both to get out of the house and to work on my coordination in my left hand. While I am mostly-ambidextrous, I still have issues with more intricate tasks with my left hand and I want to fix that. If I had time, I would probably take up cross-stitching again just to practice using my left hand.

I had a passing thought today. As I now control the household DNS, I could block websites and services that are not privacy-friendly by simply making their DNS records return NXDOMAIN results. I decided that this would be censorship though, and would therefor be an evil thing for me to do. Taking control of the //test. TLD, which IANA allocated for such use, is one thing. I should not abuse my newfound power though, even if it is only power over the machines in this one house.

I want to set up some sort of registry here within the house where any of us can register domains. I tried to find some software that takes care of that, but my search came up empty. I think that I will try building my own solution for this. I will likely use the local IP addresses of the machines on the network to determine the owner of the machines, and cause any domain registered to be bound to that person. Domains registered would then only be manageable on machines owned by that person, no password or user name required. The question is, do I want these domains to be hierarchal or not? If I choose a hierarchal modal, I will probably need to have the script set up a separate file for each second-level domain, then have it concatenate the files to rebuild the main zone file each time someone updates any of the records. If I choose a non-hierarchal model, I will probably instead have edits to the main zone file directly, and comments in the file will keep track of who owns each domain.

On second thought, maybe I will just make edits to the zone file by hand for now. I am the only person in the house that cares enough about DNS to want any domain names anyway.

I wrote in to the person in charge of scheduling appointments at the local community collage, though I do not axpect to hear back until Monday.

Speaking of email, I do not recall what my beef with Evolution is. I have not been having any trouble with Evolution this time, and it seems to be a lot better email client than Sylpheed. For one thing, I do not need to bother with Sylpheed's silly search directories; I can perform actual searches directly in my inbox. Sylpheed's in-inbox searching was highly limited. I could not even perform a basic search for emails sent to a specific one of my addresses! In Evolution, I can just enter my email address in the search bar, and the emails that I am looking for pop right up. The number of emails (read or unread) is also visible without me performing a search in Evolution. In Sylpheed, the number of emails in my inbox is only visible when I perform a search that matches at least one email, in which case I am told that X out of Y emails match, so I know that I have Y emails in my inbox.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Not Implemented Tor IP not allowed

Day 00281: Sunday, 2015 December 13

To work with the //test. TLD, I set clearnet access to my HTTPS server. It took longer than it should have due to changes in Debian's Apache package that I had forgotten about. Specifically, files in /etc/apache2/sites-enabled/ are only read if their names end in ".conf". This is idiotic. If it was like this from the beginning, that would be one thing, but this change brakes my old configuration files for no good reason. Nothing should be in that directory unless it is a symbolic link to a configuration file, so any file in that directory should be treated as a configuration file regardless of its file name, just as it used to be.

Sometimes, when I sign petition, I end up on peoples' mailing lists. Today, I got fed up with one of these lists that I am now on. The group sends my emails asking me to sign other petitions, but when I clicked on their links, I would always receive a mostly-blank page that would Not Implemented Tor IP not allowed. They even had the nerve to hide the "unsubscribe" option behind such an anti-Tor wall! This made me incredibly angry, so I wrote them a firm letter explaining that if they were going to have such anti-Tor policies, they needed to remove me from their mailing list. I also reminded them that their unsubscribe page was blocking me too, so I could not even unsubscribe myself. I have not received a response, but soon after writing, I accidentally ended up on their website again. Mysteriously, they no longer seem to block Tor exit nodes. I even tried to return several times later, and it seems that their block on Tor exit nodes is still in place, but incomplete. Their error page tells me that the block on Tor exit nodes is a direct attack on Tor exit nodes though; Tor is not being accidentally hit by this. I do not want to be involved with a group that would intentionally discourage Tor use.

I spent a good chunk of the day working in the classroom again. When we left, my mother wanted to grab a conifer for her holiday celebrations. Strangely enough, she asked that I be the one to choose the tree, despite me being the only person in the house that does not like holidays of any type. Of the trees that were shown to us, only one looked to be undamaged, so I chose that one and explained my reasoning. She seemed satisfied, so I suppose that means mission accomplished.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Odds & ends

Day 00282: Monday, 2015 December 14

I have finally managed to process all of my email. I need to make sure that I keep up with my email this time and do not fall behind again.

The person in charge of scheduling appointments at the local community collage wrote back to me saying that she would forward my message to the person that does not seem to be reachable by email. I have not yet received a response from him though.

Professor Shyguy sent out a mailing list update saying that he now has a second USB drive available for sale. This second USB drive also has his directory of "odds and ends" material that he has not otherwise made available like the first. However, for a limited time, this USB costs $10 USD} less than the first one if you preordered Fragmentation. Professor Shyguy said to email him if we wanted to take him up on the discount offer, so I took that opportunity to finally write and ask about the license of the "odds and ends" material. I was interested in the initial USB drive just to get this material, but I had not taken the time to ask yet. Below is his response.

It's free to use on any sites and such.
	 It's not exactly "creative
commons" but the "odds & ends" isn't copywritten because I don't plan on
doing anything with it.
	Thanks!
 - Brandt

On Mon, Dec 14, 2015 at 4:58 PM, y.st.
	<y@y.st> wrote:

> Greetings Professor Shyguy,
>
> I am interested in your USB offer.
	Before I buy it though, I have to ask
> about the license.
	I noticed that it contains 'a folder just full of
> "Odds & Ends"'.
	Are those covered by your usual CC BY-SA license? I am a
> free culture enthusiast, so I only buy music that is under a CC BY or CC
> BY-SA license.
>
> Thank you for the information and your great music,
> Yst Dawson

As we can see, Professor Shyguy does not seem to understand how copyright law works. Specifically, any creative work he creates is copyrighted, whether he wants it to be or not. However, he has no intention of asserting his copyright over this work, and that is good enough for me. Just to be on the safe side though, I am saving his letter here in my weblog. In the off chance that something bad happens, I have the exact wording of his permission to use this work freely.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

A black plastic shell

Day 00283: Tuesday, 2015 December 15

Yesterday after I had already finalized me weblog entry, I found that my Professor Shyguy USB drive order had not gone through. I had received an email from Discover alerting me to a charge, so I asumed that the order had been completed, but instead PayPal had sent their usual $1 USD charge that they later reverse in order to check and insure that the card is chargeable. However, in order to finalize the order, I had to click past their page that pressures users into creating a PayPal account. I had already closed the Web browser tab though and ShyGuy had already hidden the secret discount page again. Embarrassed, I had to write him back and explain that the order had not gone through and ask him to make the page available again for a little while. Today, he wrote to me saying that he is sending out orders today, and asked if I wanted a USB drive with a black plastic shell or a grey plastic shell. I had not even known that black was an option, as it is not in the photograph on the product page, but the photograph that he emailed me looked pretty good. I chose the black case.

I started some light work on a PHP/MySQL-based Web forum software project that I am tentatively calling FreeForum. Mainly, I just did some planning and note writing, but it is a start.

Speaking of PHP, I read the skeletal draft of a future proposal to make PHP case sensitive. It seems to have been started late last year and still has not seen much progress, but if completed and accepted, it would be a huge step forward! Other languages are properly case sensitive. Why is PHP not? Despite its many problems, PHP is my favorite language and it would be nice if it could become even better.

It appears that my sister will be coming over for a few days tomorrow. Additionally, it seems that all of us will be headed back to Springfield for a while on Monday.

Vanessa and Cyrus had nachos today, but they did not cook meat to go on them. When our mother found out, she became angry. She claims that because they did not have meat with this one meal, they must be trying to go vegetarian. First of all, they have meat with almost every meal, so what is the big deal if they skip the meat every once in a while? Second, there is no problem with going vegetarian. Neither of her eldest two children want to eat flesh and she knows it. However, she takes any desire to not eat the same diet as her as some sort of attack on her personally.

The local community collage did not write back today. I think that I might go back to the job hunt tomorrow. If they have still not written by Sunday, I will write to them again asking if there are any updates on my request for an appointment.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Apple and mDNS

Day 00284: Wednesday, 2015 December 16

I have been waiting to join the federated social networks until I can get the resources to host my own instances at my own domains. However, it seems that I will not have the resources any time soon. Because I have not joined these networks yet, I have been relying on nonfederated social media more that I otherwise would have. It is time to put a stop to that, so I joined some federated social networks today using other peoples' instances, despite the fact that I am unable to use my own domain when doing so. When the time comes that I am able to use my own domain for my full social presence, I will just have to cancel my old accounts that I have created today.

I started with GNU Social. Looking over a list of available instances, I found that there were several options to choose from. First, I looked for instances that used one of my favorite TLDs, the ones that do not ask for a telephone number when registering under. The only such option was at //pags.to., but anything posted at that instance has all rights reserved. That really did not seem like a good option for me. Next, I looked for instances at short domains. //bka.li. was the shortest option, but all posted content there is released under the CC BY-NC license, which is even worse. At least if all rights are reserved, I could additionally release under a free license, but if my posts are released under a nonfree license, I can still additionally release my posts under a free license, but I cannot repeal the nonfree license. The next-shortest domain that I could find a working instance at was //indy.im.. This option partially runs over HTTPS and all posts are released under a free non-copyleft license, but registration there is not available. I tried finding an option that always uses HTTPS, releases posts under a copyleft license, and has open registration, but there was no such instance on the list, at least not one that was still actually online. I eventually became overwhelmed looking for an instance with a good combination of options and just went with one of the recommended options, //gnusocial.no.. However, this instance, despite being on the recommended list does not have open registrations, so I chose //loadaverage.org. instead.

The pump.io website only listed one place to register an account, so I registered there.

To find a diaspora* pod, I looked down the main pod list for new users, though I will not link to it due to it being behind a CloudFlair anti-Tor CAPTCHA wall. Three pods on the list claim to federate not only with the diaspora* network, but also with four other social networks. Of those, one had an English interface, so that is the one I chose. Once registered, I found that posting to any of the networks that this pod connects with, I would have to already have accounts on those networks, so I did not really gain access to anywhere that I did not already have access to by choosing this pod, but at least it helped me make a decision.

Some random person just wrote to me offering to write a unique article for my website in exchange for allowing them to include a link in the article. They used the email address listed in my source code, not the email address listed on my contact page, leading me to believe that they used some sort of robot to scrape my email address. I wrote back saying that I would be happy to host such an article and link, but that the article must be released under the same GNU GPLv3+ license as the rest of my website. I am not sure if this condition will be acceptable to the writer, but if it is, my website might be getting a fresh article soon.

Theunknownman from #Volatile is starting up an Internet radio station and asked everyone to supply music for it. I have a fair library of it though, so by the time I had it uploaded, theunknownman had left. Perhaps I will be able to pass it along tomorrow. One of the things that I love about having only free music in my library is that it is completely legal for me to give away my music like this. My guess is that most of the other people giving theunknownman music are doing it illegally.

My sister came today. I talked to her about my weblog here, and asked if she had an alias that she would prefer I call her by, as it seems a bit formal to call her "my sister" all the time. She had no preference though, saying that I could use her legal name or any alias that I saw fit. A name is a very important thing though, so I cannot simply assign her an alias. Because she did not choose one herself, I suppose I will use her legal name here: Vivian. (Note: Vivian is *not* her legal name, but in 2018, she ashed me to replace instances of her legal name with this name.)

Vivian, Cyrus, and I discussed our mother and her mental state, as Vivian wants to share information about her work to help end poverty with her but fears how she will react. It is this very sort of thing that could set our mother off again. In the end, we decided that it was probably best not to mention it to our mother, as the chance of anything good coming from it was much slimmer than the chance of it blowing up in Vivian's face.

It is always nice speaking with Vivian. She helps me remember that I am not the one around here that is completely insane. She agrees with me that our mother is likely bipolar and definitely has her priorities and thought processes way out of whack.

With Vivian's Apple laptop back on the local network, I decided to try detecting it with the mdns-scan command. However, her laptop does not respond! I find this quite strange, as my current understanding is that Apple invented mDNS and her laptop does respond to its own //local. address, if you know it. It just does not respond to PTR queries to the //_services._dns-sd._udp.local. domain. I will probably look into this more tomorrow.

The school still has not written back to me. I once again made the mistake of updating my mother on the progress of this task, though it does not seem to have blown up in my face this time. She suggested going in in person to make the appointment, which was on my list of plans, but I was not going to do it just yet. Perhaps I will try walking in tomorrow and see what happens. I still think that waiting a bit longer for a return email would be a good idea before I go it, but I doubt that this should do any harm. I have already waited a couple days for what should have been a fairly quick response.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

I wish I could take a break and go to Portland with Vivian

Day 00285: Thursday, 2015 December 17

Today was far too rainy to go over to the school. I could stand the rain myself, but if I arrived wet, it might not be in my favor.

Instead, I listened to Vivian talk about the work she is doing to help end poverty. It seems that she is a volunteer for an organization called "[the Organisation]". This group helps people that want to make changes to the way things are done by giving them what they need to keep themselves and their families alive so they can focus their time and energy on improving their working conditions. This organization has chosen not to be classified as a non-profit group, because apparently, non-profit groups are prohibited from fighting the government.

Vivian's laptop battery has been dead a while, but she waited to replace it until she had a chance to speak with me in person. She thought that I would have a better chance of finding the correct replacement battery than her. Honestly though, her MacBook does not seem to have an distinguishing text printed on it that tells what model it is. How does anyone find the right battery without knowing what laptop it is? Her mDNS domain, set by the refurbishers, indicates that it might be a MacBook 6, but we are not even really sure of that. Once we had what might have been the model, I searched for a MacBook 6 battery. While I found many MacBook batteries, none of them told which model of MacBook they belong with. Are batteries interchangable between MacBook models? I have no idea. Hopefully the battery I ordered will work.

Being unable to go to the school due to the weather, I decided to spend my time filling out those change of address forms that I have been meaning to as well as begin registration for health insurance for the coming year. I found that the change of address forms were not as they had been described to me. Specifically, each form could only take a single name, not a list of names, and if desired, any mail sent to someone with a matching surname would be forwarded too. It took two forms to forward all our mail because our mother has a different surname than us. Additionally, Vivian and I were unsure of if we could have her mail sent to her home with a third form because she shares a surname with us. She opted to not even try, and instead just have her mail forwarded with ours. She says that nothing important ever comes for her at the old address.

Due to idiotic legislation by the current president of the country, we all have to register for health insurance or pay fines, even if we never go into the hospital. So today, I sat down to work on registering for gratis health care at the main country-wide health care website. However, this website maliciously discriminates against Tor users. So, I searched for the state's health care option instead. This website does not discriminate against Tor users, but uses a PDF form instead of a basic XHTML or HTML form. First, on Debian, this means downloading the form to fill it out instead of filling it out in-browser. Second, some of the fields were disabled. My guess is that they were intended to enable themselves based on which other options one selects, but that does not work so well in my PDF reader. According to my research, PDF form-filling in Linux systems is not currently an easy thing to accomplish, so it is not just me. Lastly, the PDF form contained a "submit" button, meaning that if one were to somehow fill out this for in-browser, they could submit it online, but if one is using standards-abiding and free software as I do, one must mail or fax the form in. Of course, I am against the telephone number system, so even if I had access to a fax machine, I would avoid using it if at all possible.

After filling the form out on my computer the best that I could, printing it, then completing the broken fields by hand, I set out with Vivian to the post office to mail both the change of address forms and the health care application form. Unfortunately, the rain soaked through my bag and ruined the health insurance paperwork long before we arrived. The change of address forms were fine, but we had to abort our mission. I purchased some huge plastic zipper bags though, so tomorrow should go better. It has been raining for about a month, so it will no doubt rain tomorrow too.

I asked some people online about Vivian's MacBook and the fact that it does not reveal itself to machine's performing service discovery. The person that responded said that this is due to the default firewall settings, and even explained how to set them to enable service discover. In the name of learning, I checked out her firewall, but the whole firewall was already disabled. I tried changing those settings, but it did not do any good, as the firewall was not even in use. As a last resort, I tried turning the firewall on, but this still did not make her machine respond. I changed her settings back to the way she had them, but when I went to ask about it again on IRC, I found that the network had cut me off again. It would be another several hours before I could manage to get back onto the network, so I gave up. OS X does not really interest me enough to pursue this long; the anomaly in how it handles mDNS queries just caught my attention.

Vivian discussed the possibility of taking me to Portland with her for a week or two to see what she is involved in, though neither of us could think of a way to tell our mother without her going off the deep end again. Unless we think of something, I will have to stay here in Coos Bay. This would be much easier if our mother was not so over-controlling.

I did not see theunknownman today, so I was unable to give him/her the music files. Likewise, the local community collage still has not written back.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

I may go to Portland after all!

Day 00286: Friday, 2015 December 18

The weather today was clear enough to pay a visit to the school, but due to the early-morning party, I was too tired to drop by. I could have probably made the journey just fine, but if I ended up having to talk to someone for a prolonged period of time, my lack of mental clarity today might have caused problems. Besides, I had already committed to getting the health insurance form and change of address forms delivered to the post office. By some strange coincidence, I met a man asking for directions to the post office on the way, so I was able to lead him directly there.

I finally saw theunknownman again today, so I was able to make the music handoff.

I paid the Replicant website a visit to make sure I knew what I was talking about as far as which devices were supported. While there, I found that a new system update has been available since September. Updating the system is always a pain though. First of all, because my device is securely encrypted, ClockworkMod (the recovery system) is unable to install from a ZIP file on the internal storage. However, because ClockworkMod's programmers failed to include basic ext4 support for mounting the SD card, installing from the external SD card is a huge hassle. I have to relearn how to make it work every time. Thankfully, devnull of #Volatile walked me through most of it. I ended up having to install ADB on newdawn so reach the mobile's shell, where the command to mount the external SD card for system installation was mount -t ext4 /dev/block/mmcblk1 /external_sd. While on the Replicant website, I also found that two companies are selling devices with Replicant pre-installed. Trying to get Replicant installed for the first time took several days to figure out, so having companies selling already-working devices will probably lower the barrier to Replicant adoption.

I do not understand the exact contect in which she was able to work it in, but Vivian asked our mother about bringing me to Salem with her to give our mother a break from me and work on teaching me to drive. However she did it, our mother did not freak out right away and her only stated issue is that she somehow thinks that I will have managed to start school in January, so I will be unable to leave. The school is not writing me back though, so I do not have the information that I need before I can enrol and they likely closed for winter break today. There simply is no way for me to get the information that I would need in that short amount of time. If she is to teach me how to drive though, I need to find a photography studio and get these photographs taken before we leave, assuming we will actually be able to accomplish this. Vivian lied and said that she had not yet talked to me about taking me with her, which probably helped in preventing our mother from going off the deep end, but it is sad that such a precaution was even necessary.

I received an automated letter from the Tor project saying that they appreciate the fact that I am running a relay node and that my node has now been running long enough to be considered stable. The letter also contained my Tor relay fingerprint and an invitation to register for a service that will alert me to issues with my Tor node such as my node going down or my software being out of date. It seems that when I asked my Tor instance for its fingerprint, the fingerprint was not the same one used by my node's relay activities, which is the reason it could not be found in the Atlas. It turns out that my node is in fact visible, provided you use the correct fingerprint. My node is even flagged as being fast! It is a shame that I cannot run an exit node due to my ISP being jumpy, but at least I can give something back to the Tor network.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Professor Shyguy's USB drive and Lo-Fi is Sci-Fi's music

Day 00287: Saturday, 2015 December 19

According to an email I received from the Daily Kos, the attempts in the upcoming government funding bill to defund the FCC so that they cannot enforce their net neutrality rules have been removed and do not seem to be coming back. Net neutrality does seem to be threatened though, as Jeb Bush claims that if elected, he will abolish net neutrality. Likewise, Donald Trump wants to lock down the Internet in some unspecified way. Neither of these two can be allowed to become the president of our country.

I started preparing to run eschalot on cepo, but I got distracted due to seeing a strange directory in my home directory. I think that I found the issue that caused Tor to give me the wrong fingerprint when I queried it before, though I do not feel like testing my theory right now. In my home directory on cepo, a file called ~/.tor/fingerprint. I think that in trying to find the fingerprint of my Tor instance while using a different system user than the one that Tor is running as, I caused Tor to generate a new fingerprint for my system user account.

While looking through the ~/.tor/ directory, I also found three key files. ~/.tor/keys/secret_id_key and ~/.tor/keys/secret_onion_key appear to be onion address key files while ~/.tor/keys/secret_onion_key_ntor appears to be a binary data file. I spoke with the people on #Tor though, and a user by the name kernelcorn assured me that these files are used for Tor relay node purposes; they are not in any way used for hidden services or onion addresses.

The USB drive from Professor Shyguy arrived today. The directory structure is a bit of a mess though. For the most part, things are reasonably organized, but the ./MP3s/0000 - Odds. Also ends/ directory leaves me a bit confused. For one thing, one of his Happy Parallel album is in there. It is a released album, what is it doing in the odds and ends directory? Four tracks from Triforce Tour - Triforce Collected are also in there, though the rest of the album is entirely missing from the USB drive. Supposedly, this drive contains his collective released works plus some extra, but most of this album is missing. I am also not sure how to interpret parts of this odds and ends directory because Professor Shyguy said that the odds and ends directory, which contained the otherwise unreleased works, were not under copyright, but the directory contains "Still Alive", a song that is shown on his Bandcamp account as having all rights reserved. Should I treat it as a nonfree track or a free track? To make it more complicated, the copy of the track on the USB drive claims to be part of an album called "Discography", meaning that I cannot say that this is definitely under the restrictions posted on the website, as it is an alternative releasing of the song. I have seen songs released on multiple albums where one album was entirely free, while the other album is entirely nonfree, including the duplicate track. I suppose I will put it in the nonfree group to be safe instead of adding it to my collection. Lastly, some of the tracks are only on the drive in MP3 format, meaning that to obtain either the lossless files or the Vorbis files, I will need to repurchase the respective albums online. I will probably finish going through the USB drive's files tomorrow, comparing them against the music available on his Bandcamp account, both to find what is missing and find exactly which files are most likely to fall under his "not copyrighted" claim.

The USB drive itself is kind of interesting. He took an old Game Boy cartridge, removed the circuit board, carved away most of the inner plastic shelf just inside the bottom, and used the small piece of this shelf that he left intact to hold in a USB drive by sticking the shelf fragment through the hole on the drive. The drive can now pivot into the cartridge shell for protection and pivot out for use. He also glues a tiny plastic fragment to the pivoting end of the USB drive, giving the user a place to grip the drive and send it back out, should it pivot a little too far into the cartridge. The screw in near the bottom of the cartridge seems to prevent it from pivoting way too far back. And for aesthetics, he replaced the original game label with a branded label of his own, showing his artist name, domain name, and art from his latest album. While this thing is clearly hand made (and the label even has the text "MADE IN A LIVING ROOM"), it looks like it took a lot of thought in order to figure out how to build these. They are no whimsical project; they required planning.

Cyrus was playing some music by Lo-Fi is Sci-Fi again, causing me to once again miss their music. Since my data loss back in February, I have not managed to find high-quality copies of their music. Their Bandcamp page has been removed, their website has been replaced by some "coming soon"-type page, and in every place that I knew that they once had a profile, this profile has vanished. Today, I broke down and asked Marc With a C and Chris Zabriskie about it, as they are the duo that once formed this now-disbanded band. Marc said that I should ask Chris, as it was Chris' music; Marc just played drums and sang backup. Chris said that he had to dig them out of storage, but he uploaded them to his website. Sadly, they are in MP3 format, leading me to believe that the high-quality FLAC files may be lost forever. Still, it is awesome to have songs such as I Do It 'Cause It's Right and Technology back in my music library.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Do not attempt to forward onions directly to other onions

Day 00288: Sunday, 2015 December 20

While sorting music from Professor Shyguy's USB drive, I found that Rated Heart has a new track since sometime after I purchased it. While I did not put it together right away, it seems that this track is the full version of a proprietary sample that he once released, but this time, it has been made free and added to a free album. There seems to be some gaps in this collection though. In particular, only partial copies of The Instrumentals and Triforce Tour - Triforce Collected are included and one proprietary album that I will not mention and was not going to listen to anyway was left out entirely. I will need to purchase the partial albums separately to get the full versions. I think that all the included tracks have MP3 files present, but many do not have the WAVE files that most do. Very few tracks are present in FLAC format. This USB drive sale is a better offer for people that use MP3s than for those that like myself use Vorbis files, but it is definitely nice to have the exclusive files. Some of them are older versions of songs from before they were released, but a few seem to be entirely different songs. For my sorting-by-license purposes, I decided that it was safest to consider any song to have the same license as its on-Bandcamp counterpart, even if it is an alternative version, and only take into account Professor Shyguy's "no copyright" assertion for songs unique to the USB drive. Specifically, I found these tracks to be unavailable on his Bandcamp page:

.

MP3s

0000 - Odds. Also ends

2012 - The Aeronauts - The White Lie Album

The Aeronauts - 01 - One White Lie.mp3
The Aeronauts - 02 - One White Lie 2.mp3
The Aeronauts - 03 - One White Lie 3.mp3
The Aeronauts - 04 - The Villain (Acoustic).mp3
The Aeronauts - 05 - The Aeronauts - SBF (Acoustic).mp3

2004 - Brandt Cooley - Happy Parallel

Brandt Cooley - Happy Parallel - 17 Pull Paradox (Bonus Track).mp3

Another One Bytes the Dust (Short).mp3
Professor Shyguy - Helix Prophecy.mp3
Professor Shyguy - Star Stuff (Demo).mp3

WAVs

0000 - Odds & Ends

Professor Shyguy - Helix Prophecy.wav

While building the above nested list by hand, I realized that it would have been much easier if I could have told my machine to build the list form me based on the actual structure of the directory. After I finished, I built a new function to handle this sort of situation for me next time, should I find myself in a similar situation later. I also decided to add a version number to my PHP script library. If I am going to work on building reusable code that depends on this library, such as the forum software I am going to build, I need to have version numbers so that it is easy to understand what version of the library is needed.

I logged into cepo today to get eschalot and twooni set up, and I found an interesting change. Specifically, the SSH greeting that lists where my last login was from listed the domain returned by a query of my local IP address against the rDNS entries on my local DNS server! I had no idea that the SSH server even bothered with rDNS.

I will not name any names, but someone told me that it is possible to forward a Tor hidden service port to a port on another hidden service instead of an IP address. I tried doing that, and it caused Tor to shut down entirely, costing my my relay uptime. In other words, this setup is not in fact possible. To insure that services can safely be moved away from the machine running the onion address, services should use extra encryption in addition to that provided by Tor. For example, use HTTPS with your onion addresses, not HTTP.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Flash proxies

Day 00289: Monday, 2015 December 21

While I sorted Professor Shyguy's music yesterday as far as license is concerned, it took a bit more time to prepare the tracks for use on my mobile. Specifically, I needed to rename and sort the files based on the respective track titles and album titles. I took care of that today, but found that most of the WAVE files included on the USB drive are missing their meta data. Additionally, when moving them to my mobile, I ran into a particular Replicant anti-feature again. Replicant can handle having working with case-sensitive file systems, but it fights against the intended case sensitivity of the file systems, preventing the user from actually taking advantage of it. From what I understand, Replicant inherits this abomination from Android. I never have found a way around it, besides pulling the SD card out and directly changing the file names to what they should be from my laptop. Once the files exist with their correct and case-sensitive names, Replicant reads them correctly, the only issue is getting those files in place to begin with. Furthermore, Replicant always messes with the file permissions of files on my SD card, so I always have to work with the file names on my laptop using root permissions.

I realized today that my new directory tree to XHTML unordered list translator had a fatal flaw. Specifically, a file name can contain characters that have specific meaning in XML files, but my function treated them as regular characters, allowing them to end up in the list and break the validity of the XML returned. This was an easy thing to fix though.

My mother found one of those passive mobile device signal amplifiers in her stuff, but seeing as she uses an iPhone, she was unable to make use of it. This is because the iPhones are so locked down that you cannot even open the battery compartment. In any case, she gave the thing to me.

I learned about a different sort of bridge system for Tor. Instead of using unpublished Tor relay servers, this system instead uses random peoples' Web browsers as proxies. They call this system flash proxies, and your Web browser acts as one as long as your Web browser is compatible with the system and you have a Web page loaded that contains a special flash proxy badge. Additionally, there is a Web browser plugin that allows your browser to function as a flash proxy even when no such page is loaded. I both added the flash proxy badge to my main website and installed the Web browser plugin, though adding the badge to my website was not straightforward. The problem is that the default embed code uses the obsoleted <iframe/> tag, which is not valid in XHTML 1.1. With some modification, I think that I got it working though. For anyone interested in doing the same, the code I used is below:

<object data="//crypto.stanford.edu/flashproxy/embed.html"
					type="text/html" width="80" height="15">
	<a href="https://crypto.stanford.edu/flashproxy/options.html">flash proxy</a>
</object>

My original plan was to write back to the school if they had not responded by yesterday, but I decided not to do that. I think that the school is closed for winter vacation, so I will write back to them when I think that they have opened once more.

I forgot to mention that Vivian, Cyrus, Vanessa, ans I started playing the role-playing game that Cyrus wanted to play with us. I do not want to hurt Cyrus' feelings or anything, but it really was not my cup of tea. I do much better with rules that are set in stone with no room for interpretation, such as with a computer-based game.

It seems that we are going to Springfield tomorrow. Come to think of it, I thought that the plan was to go today, but I am glad that that did not happen. I did not sleep well last night, so staying home was nice.

I have begun even more work to clean up this website in preparation for January. When I had this website tangled with my clearnet site, I used a lot of protocol-relative URIs. In fact, I modified every page on this site and the clearnet site to contain them. I think that I have removed them all from the clearnet site, but this website is much bigger. I have begun clearing them out of this place now too. To be clear, these hyperlinks are perfectly valid and point to real Web pages, they just do not fit the style of my work and should not be present on a website run by me.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Naming my relay

Day 00290: Tuesday, 2015 December 22

We headed to Springfield today, but we did not have time to run all of the errands that we had planned. Additionally, I was not able to get to the grocery store to buy the vegan bread that I wanted. Unfortunately, getting vegan bread here in Coos Bay takes way too long to be feasible, as the store that carries it is on the far side of town, so I never go buy it. I had hoped to pick the bread when we were in Springfield for that reason. I did manage to find a used blanket that appears to be warm at a thrift store though, so hopefully my nights will be less cold.

When I set up my Tor relay, I tried to name it "cepo.hn.y.st.", the FQDN of the server that runs it. However, Tor does not like the dots. Having no decent name I could give it that does not contain dots, I gave up and decided to have the server be nameless. I came up with a better idea though today, that I will probably implement tomorrow. If I am to name it, it needs to be a name unique to me, meaning that it needs to be based off of a domain, though without at least one dot, I cannot properly show which domain that the Tor relay name references. However, if I base the relay name off of an onion address, the dots do not need to be so explicit to be understood. I could either name the relay after the sixteen-character SLD of the onion address that it runs, or the SLD with "onion" appended to it, no dot needed.

I finished cleaning up the protocol-relative hyperlinks on this website when we got home, but I fear that there is still moch more cleaning to do here. I think that the next step is to find all of the links to my domain research pages and make sure that they still point to the correct pages. Twice, I moved pages in that directory, putting new pages at the URIs in which the old pages had been moved from. As a result, some of the links to specific parts of the pages now link to the wrong pages. After that, I want to work on a better navigation system that will allow one to access the preceding and following weblog entry pages from any given weblog entry page. I have a lot to fix up here and not a lot of time left in which to fix it up.

It sounds like we might be headed to the redwood forest in a couple days. I am not a fan of long vehicle trips, and sight seeing really is not my thing. Hopefully this will not be too bad though.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Major website work

Day 00291: Wednesday, 2015 December 23

I was looking at Lo-Fi is Sci-Fi's music files and found that the artist listed in the meta data is not Lo-Fi is Sci-Fi, but Chris Zabriske! At least, that is the case for three out of four of the albums. I kind of wonder if this has any significance. For example, are these files from before Chris uploaded them to Bandcamp? Bandcamp would have modified the meta data and set the artist string to "Lo-Fi is Sci-Fi". If that is the case, would these perhaps be the files that had been uploaded? If that is the case, higher-quality copies might not exist. The FLAC and Vorbis files might have been converted from the MP3s, resulting in needless bloat in the case of the FLAC files and quality loss in the case of the Vorbis files. Lo-Fi is Sci-Fi was a lo-fi band, so I would not put it past them to record in a lossy file type.

I tried to find all links in this weblog containing the text "/domain_research/#" so that I could fix them to point to the correct page, but strangely enough, grep was not returning any results for where they were. At first, I thought that special characters were being interpreted in my input string or something, but after several experiments, I do not believe that to be the case. My weblog literally has no matches for that string, so there is nothing for me to fix on that front.

Some people on IRC told me that I should discontinue use of timestamps in PHP and use DateTime objects instead. By the time that they had sugested doing that though, I had already built my new navigation helper function using timestamps. As my deadline for website cleanup completion is creeping ever closer, I will not fix my function for the time being. I will continue working on visible parts of the website and work on improving the back end source code later.

Next, I moved the navigation bar to a separate file and added support for including an arbitrary number of navigation bars to any given page. This allows me to do two things. Most importantly, it allows me to include sub-navigation options for the weblog pages by adding a second navigation bar with forward and back hyperlinks, but it also allows me to remove the English navigation bar that was present on the "choose a language" page. Fixing all the pages on the site to take advantage of this functionality was a pain though, and until the pages were fixed, the navigation bar had been removed entirely, so it could not exactly wait for another day.

It was a good thing that I had added support for arbitrary numbers of navigation bars too, as while I was finishing up coding the secondary navigation bar, I decided that it might be a good idea to add three more navigation bars to weblog entries, though I may or may not implement that. The three navigation bars would allow jumping to any year, any month in the current year, and any day in the current month. However, this may just be added bloat. First of all, these links (aside from the day-in-month links) Would link to lesser navigation pages that are kind of obsolete due to the presence of the main weblog index page. Second, the main weblog index page is linked to on every page of this site, so it would be cleaner just to keep that as the only weblog navigation link, aside from those that link to the first, last, previous, and next entries within the weblog. The again, perhaps my mult-navigarion bar idea was not so good. The navigation bar used by a given page can pull in other navigation bars from its own code as needed. Then again, having an arbitrary number of navigation bars gives me a clean way to have zero on the language selection page.

I tried naming my Tor relay "authorednansyxluonion", but Tor did not like the length of the name and shut down on me, costing me my uptime rating again. It did accept the name authorednansyxlu though. It seems that at some point, my relay stopped being considered stable, either because of this down time or the one where I tried relaying an onion to another onion, as I had been told that that was possible.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

OFTC's anti-features and WeeChat's settings

Day 00292: Thursday, 2015 December 24

OFTC has an annoying anti-feature that makes it so that if you are in a channel in which you are silenced, you may not change nicks. Additionally, they do not allow you to identify via TLS certificate until after you switch to your registered nick. And to complete this moronic mess, some channels silence users that are not identified. This means that if you autojoin these channels, you cannot identify via certificate without leaving all such channels, switching nicks, then rejoining them. This system is moronic. I tried talking to the people on the support channel, but they have no intention of fixing it. WeeChat has a feature that allows it to dynamically create nicks if your own nick is taken, such as right after a network error, which sets off this anti-feature. To be clear though, this is an anti-feature of OFTC, not WeeChat, and the feature in WeeChat is actually pretty useful on most networks. There is a way to turn it off, but until today, this feature could only be turned on or off on a client-wide basis, so the feature could not be used on networks that functioned properly and turned off for networks that are programmed to fight against the user. When asking for help getting WeeChat to treat this network differently than other networks, WeeChat's developer spoke up. He offered to move the setting to make it a network-specific setting instead of a global setting if only I would post a feature request. Within the day, he had already modified the code and closed the feature request.

A while back, I mentioned that when accessing a hidden service, you are behind six proxies: three chosen by the client and three chosen by the hidden service. However, this person corrected me, saying that there was additionally the rendezvous relay, for a total of seven proxies. However, I just found some documentation on hidden services, and found that despite my oversight, I was actually correct in the number of proxies. The rendezvous relay is actually one of the tree proxies chosen by the client.

I upgraded cepo's Debian installation today, after which Aptitude suggested that I install linux-firmware-free. I checked out that package, and it seems to contain firmware that was originally contained in the kernel's package. With my kernel package upgraded, I feared that I had lost my firmware, so I installed the package. Installing it resulted in the following warning:

W: Possible missing firmware /lib/firmware/tigon/tg3_tso5.bin for module tg3
W: Possible missing firmware /lib/firmware/tigon/tg3_tso.bin for module tg3
W: Possible missing firmware /lib/firmware/tigon/tg3.bin for module tg3

I asked on #Debian, and was told that as long as my networking functionality was still online, this was not a problem. As firmware is loaded at boot time (I think), I do not yet know for sure if I have lost the needed firmware, but hopefully everything is fine.

Supposedly, we were going to head to the redwood forest today, but it seems that that plan was canceled without my knowledge. All day, I expected us to head out, but we just did not.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

An attempt at rooting an unruly device

Day 00293: Friday, 2015 December 25

It occurred to me today that while the home page of my main website lists hashes of the site's TLS certificate, these hashes are inaccurate. The hashes are for the certificate that I used on my own server, but for security reasons, I generated a new certificate when I uploaded the website to wowaname's server. No one has pointed out the bad hashes up through now, so I can only assume that no one is checking the hashes anyway. I have removed the bad hashes, though I have not added good hashes and might not unless hashes are requested.

My mother still has not chosen what she wants done on the mobile front. I have told her repeatedly that before I can get the mobile that she wants me to carry, she needs to decide which mobile and which plan. It is clear that the mobile and plan that I chose myself is not good enough for her. However, she keeps getting on my case about it, still without making a decision. In an attempt to prevent such future arguments in the future, I purchased a cheap mobile on a cheap plan that has the stupid SMS service that she wants me to have. To be clear though, even when my Replicant was on a plan with SMS and calling features, it was not good enough for her. This secondary mobile will only alleviate her most recent gripes. If she wants me to use exactly the device she chooses, she is going to have to actually choose a device. Likewise, this device does not meet my needs, and will not in any way be a replacement for my Replicant.

I chose the cheapest device I could find, a TracFone LG Optimus Fuel, and put it on the cheapest plan I could find, a $20 USD plan that only needs to be renewed every three months. This device also has two other useful features, which are that it comes with a small microSD card and that it is rootable without the use of a Windows machine. Unfortunately, the only known rooting method I could find for this device requires the use of a proprietary mobile application. This is certainly not acceptable for my Replicant device, which needs to be free and needs to be trusted, but this secondary device is already burdened by proprietary software and can never be trusted. By rooting the device, I was at least able to make the device partially behave itself and not spy on me on Google's behalf as much.

Before resorting to the know-to-work rooting method, which requires the use of a proprietary application, I first tried modifying a free solution to meet my needs. Some software called Ghetto Root claims to be a reverse engineering of the proprietary application, though it is only known to work on one device, and it is no the one that I am working with. Like the proprietary option, Ghetto Root is supposed to install the same proprietary root access manager, so I edited the code to instead try to install Superuser, the free root access manager. I additionally added the "mod string" appropriate for my device. The installer claims success, but it seems to actually fail. After running it, I found a symbolic link at /system/bin/su, but it points to a file that does not exist and I cannot be sure that that symbolic link did not already exist. Being unable to do this the free way, and the alternative being that I walk around with a spyware-enabled device that offered no privacy or freedom whatsoever, I resorted to temporarily using the proprietary rooter, knowing that once it installed the proprietary root manager, I could swap it out for the free root manager and remove the rooting application. Before starting, I reset the device for good measure.

It is important to note that before starting, I did not activate any mobile plan and did not give the mobile access to my Wi-Fi network. I could not allow the device to phone home before the process was complete. I downloaded both the proprietary rooting application, the free Superuser application, F-Droid, Orbot, orWall, and the Xposed Installer on my laptop, not the mobile. I tried to keep my list of applications to add minimal, but felt that these five applications were justified for the following reasons. Superuser, orWall, and the Xposed installer all make changes to the /system partition, which on this device, is a pain to modify. We should be able to modify it once, then forget about it, having our changes survive even when performing a factory reset. orWall changes the system such that all Internet connectivity is broken unless orWall and a root application are present, so we need orWall and Superuser installed at all times to prevent us from having to look up complicated solutions or reinstall the applications after a system reset. F-Droid and the Xposed Installer both act as application repositories, and it would be nice to be able to install the applications we want right away instead of having to look for the repository applications first. (Please be careful about what you install from the Xposed Installer. It does not commit to keeping its repository stocked with only free applications, so many applications it contains are proprietary. Still, the application store itself and some of the applications it carries are in fact free.) Lastly, Orbot seemed like a good idea, given that orWall was already in the group. Without Orbot, orWall and Superuser could still be used to enable clearnet network connectivity, even if just long enough to install Orbot, but why not do things right instead? Why not have the Orbot installation survive system resets so that we can send our traffic through Tor from the start?

I went through the Android setup dialog, disabling automatic rotation and networking, but skipping all the input options. I quickly found that this device does not come with a file manager, making direct installation of packages placed in the file system impossible. I tried to install the application via ADB, but ADB could not find the device. I went into the device settings menu and tapped on the "build number" information rapidly until the developer options were enabled, went the the developer options menu, and enabled "USB debugging". This fixed the issue, and I was able to install the proprietary rooting application, using a command retrieved from a forum. Using instructions from another forum, I tweaked the settings of the proprietary rooting application and tried to root the device. However, the rooting application refused to perform without a network connection. My guess is that the rooting application wants to be able to phone home for statistical purposes. Being unable to route the connection through Tor, as the device was not rooted yet, I disabled or uninstalled every application that I could aside from the rooting application (so that they would have the smallest chance of phoning home), and am now waiting until I have a chance to use a public Wi-Fi point, turn on the Wi-Fi functionality, and root the device. It is unfortunate that the rooting application will probably report my hardware information such as the MAC address, as well as an IP address that pinpoints my city (or rather, the city directly touching my city), but at least it will be unable to get my home IP address or any sort of telephone number. While disabling all the applications, I found that supposedly, this device has a file manager, though I cannot find any way to access it.

I kind of want to try my hand at creating a Tor-based search engine. It has been done before, but I see no reason why I cannot build one too. If I end up gathering too much of an index though, I will probably have to shut it down out of lack of resources.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Work on my onion search engine begins

Day 00294: Saturday, 2015 December 26

Three days ago, I added a new navigation bar to my weblog pages. At that time, my compile script rebuilt all of my weblog pages. The next day, my compile script rebuilt all the pages again. Confused, I figured that I had messed something up, and that the initial rebuild had not happened for some reason. But last night, it happened again, and I now know what happened. Because I added a link to the latest weblog entry to every weblog page, every weblog page will now be recompiled every day. This is not what I wanted, but it is what I asked the computer to do. And now, being that my website is composed entirely of static files, I do not know how to remedy this. If I had dynamic files, I could have the "latest page" link always point to a single page that I update daily, one that always redirects to the latest weblog entry. I do not want to break my policy of only using static files here though. If this is the future of this website, it means two things. First, the approaching deadline of the first of next month no longer has meaningful context, and is therefor invalid, as signatures on weblog pages will be updated daily. In other words, I now have no deadline. Second, there is going to be an increasing number of disk writes done daily. It will grow to ridiculous levels. I cannot allow this to be. I need to find a way to fix this, and I need to do it by the first of the month as to not miss the deadline that fixing this preserves.

So far, I have come up with three ways to accomplish my goal of not rebuilding the entire weblog each day. The first, is to set up that redirect page that always points to the latest weblog entry. This is suboptimal because it involves adding a scripted page to a website otherwise composed of only static files. The second is to create a new page that always displays a second copy of the latest weblog entry. This is suboptimal because it involves adding a redundant page. The third idea is to use the <object/> tag in the navigation to display the ever-changing "latest entry" hyperlink. This is suboptimal because it not only stupidly puts a single hyperlink in a window in the otherwise-clean navigation, but it also will not display in text-based Web browsers. Of course, there is always the option of generating the hyperlink via JavaScript, but JavaScript should never be used for something as important as navigation. JavaScript use must *always* be optional for the user, while navigation should *always* be usable by any client that can understand basic <a/> tags.

While trying to work through what to do about my weblog pages and their incessant recompilation, I started work on my onion search engine. I could not get PHP to use a the assigned proxy for its DNS queries when using functions such as file_get_contents(). Nate from #php recommended instead using PHP's cURL functions. Accessing these functions required installing Debian's php5-curl package. While these functions worked the first time without any struggle whatsoever, they involve passing around a resource handle, which I have always thought of as a messy way to do things. Additionally, retrieving multiple Web pages requires modifying the resource handle between each Web request, which seems even more messy. The obvious answer seemed to me to build a wrapper class for the whole thing. Most of the way through, I realized that having my wrapper class behave exactly as I needed it to for today's use case was short-sighted. I had thrown in a method that behaved oddly if you were not expecting it, as it modified the resource handle in the same function call as returning data from a Web request, and I had created a strange constructor method that made for less work for me, but did not behave as the regular cURL resource handle initiation function did. I decided that the best option was to split my class into two different classes. The first class does all the cURL resource handle wrapping. It seems though that the cURL PHP module adds three types of resource handles, each with their own functions, so one class should not handle them all. This class handles only the main type, and if other resource handles are needed later, I can build more classes. The second class I built extends the first class, modifies the constructor to do what I want it to, and adds the function to modify the resource handle and retrieve a Web page.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

I think that my website cleaning is finally finished

Day 00295: Sunday, 2015 December 27

It turns out that my efforts to create a PHP-based Web page downloader for my onion search engine may have been wasted. There is already a library available that might have worked. Guzzle is available under the MIT license and has even been coded to be appropriately-namespaced. I will use my own classes that I built yesterday for three reasons though, despite their dependency on php5-curl. First, I know that my classes work. Guzzle probably works, but there is a chance that it would fail to appropriately proxy the DNS queries like file_get_contents() does. Second, I know *how* my classes work. I know how to use my classes, as I had to figure out how to build them, but I will need to start learning from scratch if I use Guzzle instead. I would like to get my onion search engine up as soon as is feasible, so learning how to use other projects that I do not need is low on my priority list. But third, and perhaps most importantly, I think that my classes can download files from more URIs than Guzzle. Guzzle works over HTTP and its encrypted counterpart, HTTPS. My classes however, are backed by cURL. I have not looked into all the protocols that cURL can use, but I did see FTP, FTPS, and Gopher on the list, all three of which might be useful if I decide to expand my search engine to include more than just HTTP and HTTPS.

I fixed up the hyperlinks in the weblog navigation bar that cause all weblog pages to be recompiled daily. My first thought today was to keep the most recent weblog entry at /en/weblog/latest.xhtml *instead of* in its appropriate place. This would have fixed the issue while also not causing duplicated content across the website. However, it would mean that weblog entries would end up pointing their "Next>" hyperlink at this address for a day, meaning that each entry page would be compiled three times: once on the first day it was posted (with no "Next>" or "Latest>>" links), once on the second day (with both links added and pointing to /en/weblog/latest.xhtml), and once in its final form (with the "Next>" hyperlink modified to point to the appropriate page). I decided instead to deal with the duplicate content and just copy the latest entry to /en/weblog/latest.xhtml. Each entry is still compiled twice, once with the "Next>" and "Latest>>" links and once without.

Having finished what I believe to be the last of my urgent website maintenance, I decided to clean up my PHP library a bit. The problem was that it was too specific to me. Parts of it were not generalized enough.

First, I fixed up the \st\y\abbr class. This class used to hold abbreviations that I use on my websites. This set of abbreviations can never be completed though, due to clashes such as "GB" (United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland) and "GB" (gigabyte). Instead, it basically is just a list of all the abbreviations that I have used at least once on one of my websites since 2015-03-07. That set is extremely arbitrary and will likely not fit most people's needs, so it should not be built into a reusable class. I have now stripped all abbreviations from the class itself, and instead programmed some simple logic that allows the class to parse the needed abbreviations out of either a file or an array. Due to the data format that I want to use, abbreviations needed to be accessed via keys that are sometimes not allowed in function names, meaning that my old method of accessing abbreviations would not do. I reprogrammed the class to allow access via array-like indexes, which broke every page that uses abbreviations on both of my websites. It was a major pain to go through every page fixing all the errors, but two good things came of this. First, instead of containing arbitrary abbreviations that may or may not be of help, the class now allows the user to specify any abbreviation that is needed. Second, the PHP library will not have to be updated with each little abbreviation I need to add. As an added bonus, setting up alternate abbreviation translations for use on other-language sections of the website should be a breeze now, when the time comes. It will take some time getting used to the new abbreviation syntax that I need to use in my weblog entries though.

Second, I worked on tuning up the \st\y\weblogentry() function. This function treats an arbitrary date that is related only to this one weblog as somehow special. It needed to be generalized better. This was impossible to accomplish cleanly in a function, so I upgraded it to a class. The function name has been bothering me for a while, as it does not match the style of my other function/class names, so because changing the function into a class would break all direct references to it anyway, I changed the name to \st\y\day_number. This class now takes a year, month, day, and zero-padding level to use when instantiating. Due to a glitch in the initial programming of this class, many pages may have been recompiled needlessly. However, once I had the error fixed, only the reference to the old function in the main compile script needed to be fixed. No other direct references to that function exist, and an object of this class is a drop-in replacement for the string variable I had been using to call the function previously. I have a feeling that this class will need to be modified slightly to accommodate translations to other languages later.

Greatly needing a break, I took a short walk looking for an open Wi-Fi connection that I could use to root my secondary device. I quickly found that because the Web browser was disabled, I could not use captive portals. This ruled out practically ruled out all the open Wi-Fi connections that are run by businesses and *want* guests using their Wi-Fi as a way to draw in customers, so I instead focused my efforts on finding a residential hot spot that someone had not bothered to secure. After all, if they really wanted people to stay off their Wi-Fi connection, they would have put in place either a password or a MAC address whitelist. It is not hard to do either. Sure enough, I found one, and quickly rooted the device. I will save further work on the device for another day, quite possibly tomorrow.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The spider's first run

Day 00296: Monday, 2015 December 28

For my new search engine to be at all effective, it needs to know how to handle relative URIs. It obviously cannot request pages with them directly, so I built a function that takes a base URI and a relative URI and merges them to form a new absolute URI. I found that PHP's parse_url() function was very helpful for breaking URIs into their components so that they could be merged. However, all accounting for . and .. directories, as well as all processing of the URI components to form the new absolute URI, had to be coded by hand. It took several hours to get it right, but I think that my new function does what I need it to now.

My next task was to find a way to find hyperlinks in a downloaded page so that the URIs can be collected, normalized, and added to the database. I thought that this task would be more difficult than the task of normalizing relative URIs, but I was pleasantly surprised. PHP's xml_parse_into_struct() function performs most of the leg work. This function's output will also make it easy to take into account the page's preferred base base URI, a feature that I wanted to add way later, but will now be able to build very early on. I was worried that this would only work on XHTML pages, as HTML is not XML-compliant, but it also seems to work on the few HTML pages that I tested it on. Like the curl_*() functions, the xml_*() functions require passing around a resource handle, so I wrapped them up in a class as well.

I quickly found a strange issue with the new class though. Each object instantiated from it can only be used to parse a single XML document. I do not think that this is an error in the class, but rather, an issue with the underlying PHP functions, and in fact, I witness the same behavior when I remove my wrapper class.

I performed my first trial run of the search engine's spider today, and at first, it seemed to be doing very well. However, it found a large file that someone had linked to and it got stuck there. I think that it ate all the memory of my machine, too, as my machine ended up locking up entirely after a couple hours of being stuck on this one file. I considered screening the Content-Type headers of files before downloading them, but the particular file that clogged up the spider claims to be of type text/plain; charset=UTF-8. It was not a text file though, it was an XZ compressed file. Headers cannot always be trusted, as servers can be misconfigured. However, I think that the real threat is not misconfigured servers, but maliciously-configured servers. I should not rely on headers for anything as important as keeping the spider unclogged. There does not seem to be a direct way to limit file download size, but someone on IRC gave me a hint as to how to set a download limit in a less direct way. It seems a little confusing to me, potentially because it has been a long day, so I will try working with this again tomorrow.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Fixing my spider

Day 00297: Tuesday, 2015 December 29

This morning, the code at Stack Overflow looked much more manageable than last night. I built a new class based on it that takes a size in bytes during instantiation, then uses that size as a reference when the object is called as a function. The example instead used a closure, but I think having a single line such as CURLOPT_PROGRESSFUNCTION => new curl_limit(1024*1024), is much more readable. I opted not to set CURLOPT_BUFFERSIZE, as I do not know what that is supposed to do. I think that it somehow makes cURL progress reports come more frequently, from what the question/answer page was saying, but I do not need that. I do not need an exact cut off point, just a way for the download to be prevented from going completely wild. I set the download limit to a full megabyte hoping that that would be a high enough limit to allow all regular Web pages to come through, and so far, that seems to be fine. No downloads were aborted aside from that singular problem file. After getting past that though, the spider quickly ran out of pages to crawl. It seems that this website does not link to any onion-based websites that link to many others. I will try linking to Harry71's Onion Spider robot to improve the results I get. I fear that this much input could jam something up on my end though. My own spider is not at all optimized and it keeps all its known onion addresses in memory at once. This entry will be put up prematurely so that i can continue my experiments.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

After some more testing, I realized that I needed a couple new features. The first breaks unneeded relationships between URIs by sorting the database before saving it. The second is more necessary for basic functionality though. I found that the spider was repeatedly requesting the same page Harry71's website using different URI fragments. We do not need to request the same page several times, nor do we want URI fragments to be in our database. A quick search of the existing database showed that there were only two fragments already in the database from the first successful run. One was a legitimate anchor that I embedded in a page, but the other was an error in my weblog. It confused me at first that the bulk of my anchors were not being found by the spider, but I soon realized that it is because those anchors are on pages accessible over the clearnet.

These two new features in place, I ran the spider once more, starting again from the single-entry database that i had started with. Because the first-run database was created today, I figured it would be easier than trying to hand-edit the database to remove the two entries containing fragments. The database is currently stored as a serialized array, and last time that i tried editing one of those by had, I kept breaking it. After the spider ran a while, I noticed that it was converting some relative URIs to the incorrect absolute URIs. It seems that I need to account for the special case of files being present in the website's document root while also linking to relative URIs. I took care of that error, and while I was at it, added a configurable user agent string. On the next run, quite a ways in, I found that the <base/> tag was not being properly handles, and once again, I had to restart the spider over.

While speaking with theunknownman on Volatile, he asked how my website was put together, so I separated the personal stuff that I do not want in a clearnet repository out into a separate repository, bound the two repositories with symbolic links, and uploaded the main compile scripts and templates.

On a more serious note, wowaname and lucy are hassling theunknownman on #Volatile. Theunknownman had some sort of technical issue with his VPN, and instead of preventing an IRC connection from being established, his machine connected to the network over clearnet. Now they are flaunting the fact that they have his home IP address, much to his terror. He thinks that they will actually do something to him now that they know where he is. I do not think that theunknownman is in any real danger, but this shows just how much of a troll wowaname can be. She has most of the channel hassling theunknownman simply because she can.

I am hanging out with a band of trolls. I need to find better company to keep. It is difficult though when most places maliciously discriminate against Tor users. It seems that trolls are pushed into the few places that allow Tor use, as they use Tor to evade bans. Those of us that do not evade bans, and if fact have done nothing to get banned, get blocked as collateral damage.

Yesterday, the letter saying that mail having my surname would be forwarded to out new address finally came. Today, we actually received our forwarded mail too, complete with spam. It seems that the mail forwarding has been set up successfully.

My end-of-day progress with the spider did not go as planned. It got stuck on costeirahx33fpqu.onion for some reason. I waited several hours, but it would not budge. I will need to tinker with it more tomorrow to try getting past that issue. I might set a time-based timeout to take care of it, as I do not think that this was a large file issue like last time.

I learned something interesting from synapt of #php today. Apparently, the architects behind PHP were not even halfway done writing PHP6 and people were already writing documentation and even books about how to code in it. This documentation and these books were obviously inaccurate, as there was no way to know yet how PHP6 would turn out, so PHP6 was canceled altogether to to avoid the confusion that these people had caused. Now, the developers are instead working on PHP7, giving it the features that PHP6 was going to have.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

accessed574tizbu.onion.

Day 00298: Wednesday, 2015 December 30

The first thing I did today was get my new onion address set up: accessed574tizbu.onion.. This onion address now runs on my laptop and takes care of anything that is better done on my laptop than on my server. What that mainly means is that I now have a local onion address for use with TorChat, which causes TorChat clients used by other people to stop sending my client messages when my machine is down. That should prevent some data loss.

With my onions sorted out, I next set up ngIRCd from the Debian repository. I tried to set up Atheme services to go with it, but I never did get that set up properly. It seems that the version kept in Debian's repository is too old to function with ngIRCd. I took a look at some other options but it seems that only two of the major IRC daemons actually implement the standard, and of those, the original IRCD appears to use a custom extension to the protocol or something. Honestly, seeing as I care about standards, ngIRCd seems to be the only IRC daemon for me. However, it would be nice to not pull in outside software. If I switch to Ratbox, I can just install the Ratbox-specific IRC services package with it.

Theunknownman was having strange issues when trying to connect to the IRC server though. In truth, we never did figure out what the problem was, but after spending most of the day trying to fix it, we finally did. The settings that worked were the same settings that he had tried several times before. We were both confused by the end of it, and I think that we were both a bit frustrated.

Yesterday, I was unable to retrieve a specific email that I tried to read, but I figured that the email had just been corrupted or something. However, I found out today that that was not the issue. Instead, I am not able to retrieve mail from the server at all in Evolution now. It seems to be specific to this client, other clients do fine. I tried clearing Evolution's cache, but that did not help at all. Instead, I now cannot see any of the directories on the mail server. The specific error message is Error fetching folders: syntax: expecting 's', found 'c', whatever that means. I have submitted a request for help on the Zoho forums, but it appears that my post hit some sort of moderation queue, potentially because this is my first post there. I hope to hear back soon though. Evolution has most of my email held locally, so I cannot migrate away from it so easily, especially if it is not functioning well enough to put my email back on the server where I can get to it.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Wrapper classes

Day 00299: Thursday, 2015 December 31

This morning, I awoke to find that our home's Internet connection was down. Everything seems to be fine on our end, leading me to believe that the problem is on our ISP's side. In any case, it got me thinking. I am pretty helpless without the Internet. This morning, I was not able to accomplish anything of note. I could not test my email client to see if everything is in order now. I could have worked on my search engine spider, but the point of that thing is to learn. I do not already know the functions and parameters I need in order to make it work. Without access to the online PHP manual, I could not continue progress. Likewise, I considered starting a small project to fill the time by building wrapper classes for as many PHP function sets as I could that pass around a resource. However, again, I would need the PHP manual in order to find and understand these function sets. I could not work on the IRC server either, as it appears that I do not have the software needed to do so. The IRC server is up and running perfectly already, so the only thing left to do is get services running. My current services software is incompatible with my current IRC daemon though. I need to install a new services package and/or a new IRC daemon, which requires retrieving it or them from the Internet. At the very least, I need to download the PHP manual. I can put one copy of it at https://php.test/ for easy use when my local network is functioning but we cannot access the greater Internet, as well as a second copy on my laptop hard drive, where it willl not be as convenient to use, but will be perfectly accessible even when I have no connection at all.

While trying to figure out what to do with myself, I realized that the PHP wrapper class would be a good project for me. While it would be incredibly simple, it would also teach me about the different resource types available in PHP. At the very least, I make direct use of two different resource types in my code, and I really should clean that up with some object-oriented code. I also think that I should move my wrapper classes to a sub-namespace, making them easy to identify both in my code and in my directory tree. That was when it hit me. I could download the PHP manual on my mobile, then transfer it to my laptop over MTP.

I thought that I would need to grep the manual to find informations on all the resource-using functions, but much to my delight, ./php-chunked-xhtml/resource.html has a list of them. Most of the entries on the table there have hyperlinks to the sections of the manual that document the functions, though a few do not. Having no access to the Internet on my laptop, it was easiest to just assume that the links were not present due to there not being any entries in the manual, and instead focus only on the resource types that did offer links to their related functions.

First, I made the modifications necessary to move my existing wrapper class, the one for cURL resources, into the sub-namespace. After that, I turned my focus to attention on GnuPG handles. Much to my surprise though, the gnupg_init() function and the handles that it creates were not mentioned in the manual. I would have suspected that functions that are not built-into PHP are mentioned only on the online manual if not for the fact that cURL resource handle and accompanying functions are in fact listed in this manual. In any case, adding a wrapper class to GnuPG would have to wait until I had Internet access again. My next target was the objects output by the dir() function. According to the manual, dir() is only used as pseudo-object oriented method of accessing directories. However, I found that the class of objects output by this function is completely legitimate. Unlike the class used by closures, you can even instantiate this class with the new key word. It even has all the functions that one would expect it to have, with the exception of two: a constructor and a destructor. The dir() function acts as a sort of pseudo-constructor though, and a destructor is not strictly needed. I decided not to try extending this class, as it would pretty much just mean changing the line $var = dir($file); into the longer line $var = new dir($file);, which would need to be preceded by a second line reading use st\y\wrapper\dir; for the first line to even be that short. My guess from reading the documentation is that the dir() function basically acts like this:

<?php
function dir($directory, $context=null) {
    $new = new Dir;
    $new->path = $directory;
    $new->handle = opendir($directory, $context);
return $new; }

It might have some input checks in it unlike the code above, but aside from that, I think that it behaves about the same way.

Before I could get any actual new classes written, I was whisked away to work in my mother's classroom for most of the day. On the bright side though, it sounds like I can probably go to Portland with Vivian with minimal problems attached! I will likely stay there for three weeks. During that time, I may or may not be able to update my canary. This should be awesome though, I will get to see what she is doing to make a difference in the world and hopefully even help.

It looks like I was not the only one having mail issues, but Zoho fixed the problem! It looks like tha other two users that joined the conversation were using the same mail client as I, though I did not mention what mail client I use. After posting about the issue, I realized that I should have mentioned that I was using an IMAP client.

While out today, I realized that I should work on the directory wrapper, despite my initial decision not to. In the case of the way that the built-in directory class and directory functions work, they are really only useful when a complex iterative loop is built around them. The class should be able to iterate over itself, or at least work well in a simple loop. I quickly found the likely reason that iteration was not included in the built-in class though. The directory resource handles are not built in a way that makes using the Iterator interface easy. Putting these wrapper classes together has proven to be quite boring though, so I do not think I want to sit down and complete them all at once. Instead, I will make sure to complete at least one to throw in with each regular update I perform on my library.

I found a dbx extension for PHP in the manual while looking for functions that need to be wrapped. The documentation says that instead of a resource, an object is passed around between functions. Why are these functions not made object methods? It might be worth extending the class used and add the methods in, but testing the name of the class used is undocumented and and finding out from PHP itself would require setting up some sort of database so that the class can be successfully instantiated using the provided functions and the object class checked with the get_class() function. I only managed to get four new wrapper classes built today, but I will continue the project later.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.